<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first and chief groundes of architecture vsed in all the auncient and famous monymentes with a farther &amp; more ample defense vppon the same, than hitherto hath been set out by any other. Published by Iohn Shute, paynter and archytecte.</title>
            <author>Shute, John, d. 1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1563</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101701</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837509</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1835</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12159)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1835)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1008:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first and chief groundes of architecture vsed in all the auncient and famous monymentes with a farther &amp; more ample defense vppon the same, than hitherto hath been set out by any other. Published by Iohn Shute, paynter and archytecte.</title>
                  <author>Shute, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], xviii [i.e. xvii] leaves : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Fletestrete nere to Sainct Dunstans churche by Thomas Marshe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1563.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Number xiii omitted in folio numbering.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Architecture --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST AND CHIEF GROVNDES OF ARCHITECTVRE vſed in all the auncient and famous monymentes: with a farther &amp; more ample diſcouſe vppon the ſame, than hitherto hath been ſet out by any other.</p>
            <p>PVBLISHED BY Ihon Shute, Paynter and Archytecte.</p>
            <p>¶ IMPRINTED AT London in Fleteſtrete nere to Sainct Dunstans churche by Thomas Marſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1563.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:2"/>
            <head>¶THE CONTENTES OF THIS BOOKE briefly collected &amp; ſet out for the helpe of the Reader.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He diſcourſe from time to time howe this ſcience of Architecture hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed. Folio. i.</item>
               <item>VVhat the office and duetie is, of him that wilbe a perfecte Architecte or maiſter of buildinges. Folio. iii.</item>
               <item>The firſt piller that was found out by the Ionians, vppon the ſimetrie of a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man, being <hi>6</hi> times the length of his foote in height, was renewed again by the Tuſcanes, and of them taketh his name to be called TVSCANA. Folio. iiii.</item>
               <item>The ſecond piller called DORICA builded to his perfection in Grece, by Dorus, and of him taketh his name whoſe height is <hi>7</hi> times his thiknes whiche thicknes is called the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter. Folio. vii.</item>
               <item>The third piller called Ionica was ſet in the temple of Apollo, and Diana finiſhed and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Ionians, whoſe height is <hi>8</hi> times his thicknes. Folio. ix.</item>
               <item>The fourth piller called Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nthia, found in the citie of Corinthe by Calimachus the excellent Architect, whoſe height is <hi>9.</hi> diameters. Folio. xi.</item>
               <item>The fifth piller named Compoſita or Italica made to his perfection in the time of Vaſpaſian by the auncient Romaynes, whoſe height is <hi>10.</hi> diameters. Folio. xiiii.</item>
               <item>Of another auncient piller, neceſsarye to the before named pillers found out to his perfection by the Atheniens called Atticurga or Atica. Folio. xvi.</item>
               <item>The placing of the fiue orders, namely, AREOSTYLOS, DIASTYLOS, EVSTYLOS, SISTYLOS, and PICNOSTYLOS. Folio. xvii.</item>
               <item>A rule of Vitruuius geuen for theſe thre pillers, Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia, for the placinge or diſplacing of them one aboue an other. Folio. xviii.</item>
               <item>A rule for the diminiſhing of the piller vnder the Capitall. eodem.</item>
               <item>An example to be obſerued for the increaſe of the height of Epiſtilium. eodem.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>¶ Faultes eſcaped in the printing are thus to be corected.</head>
            <p>In folio. ii. line. i. a. for Forence reade Florence.</p>
            <p>In folio. vii. line. xxxiiii b. for Trochitus, reade Trochilus.</p>
            <p>In folio. xi. line. ii a. for Calimachius, reade Calimachus.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE MOST HIGH AND EXCELLENT Princes Elizabeth by the grace of God Queene of England, Fraunce, &amp; Ireland, defendor of the faith. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is both rightly and excellently affermed of Marcus Tullius Cicero, in his firſt booke de officijs (right Excellent Princes &amp; my moſte gratious ſouerayne Lady) that no man is borne into this wolrd for his priuat and ſinguler weale, becauſe our Countrie chieflie, partely our parents, &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our kinsfolke do require as it were a duety of vs, &amp; recompence for that the whiche we haue receiued and like as the members of mans body be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers in number, and haue according to their diuerſitie diuers and peculier properties ſo is it in a good and well ſetteled co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men weale: in whiche ther is no office ſo baſe, or handie worke ſo ſimple whiche, is not neceſsary and profitable for the ſame. And as the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body doing without impedimentes their naturall dueties, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body is in an helth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hermonye, &amp; able to performe all that belongeth to the ſame. So is it in a publike weale whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all men in their calling, do labour not onely for their owne gayne, but alſo for the profit and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of their Countrie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which thinges when I according to my ſmall Capacitie did waye with my ſelfe, I was as it were ſtirred forward to do my duetie vnto this my Countrie wherin I liue and am a member. And ſo much the rather, for that being ſeruant vnto the Right honorable Duke of Northu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <hi>1550.</hi> It pleaſed his grace for my forther knowledg to mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine me in Italie ther to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the doi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkilful maiſters in architectur, &amp; alſo to view ſuch au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Monumentes hereof as are yet extant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whervpon at my retourne, preſenting his grace with the fruites of my trauailes, it pleaſed the ſame to ſhewe them vnto that noble king Edward the vi. your maieſties moſt deare brother of famous memorie, whoſe delectation and pleaſure was to ſe it, and ſuche like. And hauing the ſayde trikes and deuiſes aſwell of ſculture &amp; painting as alſo of Architecture, yet in my keping, I thought it good at this time to ſet fourth ſome part of the ſame for the profit of others, eſpecially touching Architecture: wherin I do followe not onelye the writinges of learned men, but alſo do ground my ſelfe on my owne experience and practiſe, gathered by the ſight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Monumentes in Italie. And becauſe all the members of the body haue cheflye and principally a duetie to the head, as gouernour of the whole, and without which, al the other can not liue. So my duety inforſeth me moſt ſoueraigne lady (the perfect &amp; natural head next vnto God of this our common weale,) to ſhew a token of the ſame vnto your highnes, in preſenting theſe my poore and ſimple laboures whervnto I am the rather boldned conſidering your highnes delight in all kynd of good learning, and parfect ſkill in the tonges and ſciences Moſt humble beſeching your royall maieſtie to vouchſafe to let this my ſmall trauaile and woorke paſse vnder your noble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and defence: and I according to my bound and duety ſhall pray to God for your long life and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Raygne, with peace and tranquilitie to his honour and glorie. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties moſt humble and obedient ſubiecte. Iohn Shute.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:3"/>
            <head>¶ IOHN SHVTE PAINTER AND Architecte: vnto the Louing and freindly R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aders.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongeſt al other thinges (gentel &amp; louing reader) wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of almightie God hath moſt liberally, and plentifully endewed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: there is nothing eyther for the dignitie and worthines of the thynge ſelfe, or for the wonderfull eſtimation and price whiche in all times it hath bene in, more excellent, pretious, and comendable then learnyng knowledge and ſcience, the which alone cauſeth mortall men to be moſt like immortall Goddes: and as it taketh out of their mindes that rude and vncomely admiration wherwith through ignoraunce the ſimple in moſt vaine trifles are wonderfullye occupied. Jo to the wiſe be monumentes and woorkes ſkilfully practiſed and carfullie left both commendable &amp; merueilous: yea and ſuche, as neither the iniuries of any ſtormes and tempeſt can cleane waſt and conſume, no nor (as it ſemeth) the enuie of man or ſpoyle of enemies deface &amp; ouerthrow, neither that which is grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſte of all, time it ſelfe can deface or caſt out of mynde. And amongeſt all other ſtudies there is none in my ſimple iudgement of this ſorte that diſerueth greater prayſe, then that whiche is of the grekes named Architectonica, and of the latines Architectura (I thinke not altogither vnfite nor vnaptlie by me termed in Engliſhe, the arte and trade to rayſe vp and make excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent edifices and buildinges) the whiche like as in all other ages before hath bene in meruelous accoumpte and eſtimation, as ful wel appereth by diuers learned Philoſophors and famous prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that imbraced y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, as Plato, Ariſtotel, Plini, who were excellent therin as their workes will witneſse. Allexander Magnus. Iulius. Ceſar, Veſpaſian, Adrian with many other auncient greckes and Romaines which laboured to aduaunce their name therby who lefte many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of their vertue, hygh intentes and doinges by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame with many other famous, of which Plini, maketh mention. Vitruuius and Frontyne, of later dayes men prayſe worthy very ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and painfull therin So in vs ſemeth it not only to craue the wonted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation, but alſo to be moſt neceſsarie and profitable aſwell by the condition of the time as neceſsitie of the thing it ſelfe. And ſurely ſuche is the amplitude and largnes (I may well ſay perfection) of this facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that without ſum acquaintaunce with many other artes ye ſhall not enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> depe ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: for it hath a natural ſocietie and as it were by a ſertaine kinred &amp; affinitie is knit vnto all the Mathematicalles which ſciences and knowledges are frendes and a maintayner of diuers rationall artes: ſo that without a meane aquaintance or vnderſtanding in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neyther payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, maſsons, Gold ſmythes, enbroderers, Caruers, Ioynars, Glaſsyers, Grauers, in all maner of metalles and diuers others moe can obtayne anye worthy praiſe at all Nowe all theſe being braunches of that forſayd foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtocke, or ſcience ſhall bring forthe the frutes of it to their great profites, and Commoditie of the Realme, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing and through lye practiſed in the ſame) by time ſhall increſe riches, worſhippe, and ſame. Conſidering with my ſelfe the many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold commodities and profites that ſhould redownde to a great many louers of the ſame, and contrary wiſe what aloſse and hinderaunce it hath bene to them that lacke the langwages &amp; learning who of neceſsitie hath remained in ignoraunce to theyr great loſse and diſcomodity of the Realme. Notwithſtanding I know well there hath bene a multitude and at this time be very many lerned men who hath (throughe trauaile receiued) the ful perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the prudent
<pb facs="tcp:1835:3"/> lady Scientia, of whom ſo depely learned I craue pardon for my rude raſhnes that I hauing but taſted a certaine ſwetenes of her excellencie and liberalitie, wherfore naturall loue hath drawne me to aduaunce her reputation and honour, according to my poore abilitie and good wil, the thinge nothing garniſhed as it ought to be but moſt briefly and playnelye with ſuche demonſtrations that it might edifie them which of a long time haue deſired and reached at it to attaine Alſo for the encoraging of thoſe which erneſtly ſtudied and fauored it. I thought it therfore good to ſette out and commit to writing in our natiue language, parte of thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche (both by great labour and trauaile, at the firſt for my priuat commoditie I ſearched out and for my owne pleaſure out of diuers aſwell latin and Italian, as french and dowche wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) I haue diligenly gathered. As alſo paſsed many countries and regions to ſee, both in Rome amongeſt the antiquities and in the moſt notable places of Italie, where are moſt excellent buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinges, and intending to write of Architecture or buildinges: I thought it beſt neither with the lighteſt or leaſt profitable parte therof to beginne, nor altogither after the moſte ſlender ſorte to handell that which I purpoſed to intreate vpon. I haue therfore taken my firſt ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce into the writing of this arte, at the fiue antique pillers or Columnes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly-named of the places and perſones partely where and of whom they were inuented, and partely of their vertues &amp; properties of thoſe that they wer likned vnto, which pillers names are theſe as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Tuſcana, Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia &amp;, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſita, The treatiſe of theſe pillers, as it hath in it moſt delectation and pleaſure in the beawtie and comlines of the workmanſhip appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vnto them ſo though at the beginning, it be mingled with a littell aſperitie and as it were bitternes (for the dificultie and hardnes wherwith as both principalles and alſo other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of any excellencye at the firſt are couſtomed to be, it is ſomewhat Comberous) yet it is both ſo neceſsary and profitable, that neither without it any man may attaine to any eſtimable part of the reſte of this ſcience, and with it as by a klew of thred or plaine path way a man may moſt eaſsely pearſe and lightely paſouer the moſt darke &amp; vnknowen corners of the whole proceſse therof. But to ſpeake of the worethines of this parte of Architecture: it ſemeth almoſt altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperfluous, wherfore taking theſe to ſuffice in the part to be ſayde, I will now ſhew what trade and order I do followe in the declaration of the meaſures, proportions, and garniſhmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of theſe before mencioned pillers. For ſo much therfore as in teaching of all artes thre thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are chiefly to be conſidered that is to ſay diligence in geuing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preceptes, aptnes in choſying plaine and euidente examples, and laſt of all practiſe and experience of the teacher. I haue for the firſt parte taken for my author chieflye to be followed the noble and excellent writer Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truuius one of the moſt parfaicteſt of all the Antiques, and for that, neither any one man in what arte ſo euer it be is abſolute, and that other ſinguler men of the Antiques and he in many poinctes do diſagre and differ (which Sebaſtianus Serlius, a meruelous conning artificer in our time) in many places of his workes learnedly doth declare. I haue added vnto him vpon what ſoeuer in any thing ſemed nedfull the opinion and meaning of the ſayde experte writer Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus, here and there alſo wher I thought meete I haue ioyned the minde and iudgement of one Gulielmus Philander a notable man whiche about the yere of oure lorde. <hi>15.6.</hi> wrote vnto the frenche king Anotacions vpon Vitruuius, concerning this matter or ſuche like. Now for examples which are neceſsarily required to the opening of ſuch darke matters, I haue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where through the whole proceſe of this preſent treatiſe after the preceptes to the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:1835:4"/> of them ſette both demonſtrtion and figure, and as for practiſe and experience of theſe thinges whiche I teache, I aſsure the moſte gentle reader and all other that ſhalbe readers fo this my littel worke that I haue put no title in any part therof co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſimetry to vſe the accuſtomed terme of the arte of the fornamed columbes, whiche I haue not aſwell ſeene and meaſured in Italie, from whence they cam firſt vnto vs amongeſt the Antique woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as read and ſtudied in England in the Antentique writers, that I might with ſo muche more perfection write of them as both the reading of the thinge and ſeinge it in dede is more then onely bare reding of it. This ſmall and ſimple treatiſe of myne I can not tell whither with like felicitie brought to his parfection as with no ſmall laboure and ſtudie for this time ended, I thought meete as the firſte frutes of my poore attemptes &amp; indeuors to leue as a duetye and dette of me to be payde, and that well receiued of all men, I ſhall thinke my ſelfe moſt happye, and if not of all perſones, yet at the leaſt wiſe of ſuche as be honeſt eſtemers and accepters of other mennes diligence and ſtudies. The which if it come to paſse, both I ſhalbe glad of my laboures in theſe thinges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed and for the loue of my naturall Countrimen be further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more incouraged hereafter to attempte greater thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Thus almightie God preſerue the in godly excercices to his pleaſure for euer Amen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:4"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:5"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:1835:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">¶The diſcourſe from time, to</hi> TIME HOVVE THIS SCIENCE of Architecture increaſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning of the world, Nature by neceſſitie dyd firſte inuent ſtraunge maner of couertures or houſes for the people to inhabyte in. But of all ſuche order and forme of buyldinges as were before Noes fludde, it ſhall not nede to make reherſall. But after the fludde of Noe, the people agayne, when they were increaſed and multiplied, did daylye more and more, ſeeke for theyr commoditie to be defended from the heate of the Sunne, and coldeneſse of the ayer: ſome ſuccoured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vnder the ſhadowe of trees, and other taking occaſion thereby, deuiſed to ſet vp forked ſtakes, with the forkes vp wardes, and there vpon layed bowes. Afterwardes they ſtill deuiſed and daylye did practiſe more and more in that kinde. And in time, they perceyuing the vſe of cutting with yron, did ſet vpright trees as they had before, wyth theyrſtakes being done with their handes, and by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhould not cleaue witth the heauines of theyr burdens aboue at the toppe, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed them about wyth ringes of Yron, and called them Pillers or Columnes. The forme and ſhape of which Pillers, they did imitate, faſhioning them of ſtone. And then they callynge to theyr remembraunce the fludde of Noe, which had drowned all the world, deuiſed to build the to wre of Babilon. So they added in ſteede of the rynge aboue at the toppe of their pillers, theſe, which our author Vitrinius calleth Aſtragali, and Apophigis. So in proces of time, diuers witty men euer addinge ſome thinge thereto, at the laſt it came to ſome perfection. Then did they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to deuiſe and practiſe after dyuers faſhions, and buylded a great parte of the tower. In which buylding came the deuiſion of tounges, or languages, whereby theſe buylders were par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and ſcattered abrode vpon the face of the earth, and inhabited many ſtraunge countreyes, and began to buylde in Egipte, and after that in many other places, as ſemeth by the workes, which Belus, Ninus, and Semiramis buylded, which were ſpred ſo farre, as ſom men do ſuppoſe that Trier in lowe Doutcheland ſhould haue bene buylded of the brother of Ninus as ye may perceyue by Beroſus, Herodotus, and many other that are writers and witneſses of the ſame. Yea, ſhortly after was made Memphis, the whiche nowe is named Alkayre, the whiche was buylded by a kinge of Egipte, hauing in compaſse round about, one hundred and fiftye ſtades, or as ſome interpretate it, ſo many furlonges, and in like maner the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t citie of Thebes in Grece, beſides many other cities, which were made before and after. In the which it is to be ſuppoſed, that there were ſumptuous temples and Pallaces. So, that they were experte and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan in the ſcience to come to more perfection. And immediately after a wittie man named Dorus (the ſonne of Helemer and Optix the Nymphe) inuented and made the firſte piller drawen to perfection, and called it Dorica, after his owne name. Shortlye after him, there was Iôn, ſonne of Xuthus, that was made gouernour of a part of Caria, which he had wonne, he in that countrey buylded theſe cities folowing, Priem, Samum, Teorem, Colophonem, Nachiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Erithren, Phoceam, Clazomenas, Lebedum, Melyten, of the which, the citizeins afterwardes draue out of that countrey the Caryans, and called it Ionia, after theyr kinges name, and then they made their churches and Temples of their Goddes, and firſt began with Appollo his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:1835:6"/> as they had ſene it in Grecia before. And they not knowing any meaſure of pillours conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered howe to make a iuſt Symetrie, that it might be comely and alſo ſtronge, toke their meſure by the foote of a ſtronge faſhioned manne, findinge him to be in height ſixe times, the length of hys foote, and ſo by that meſure finiſhed all the partes of that piller, and called it Dorica, bycauſe they hadde ſene it in the workes of Dorus, and ſo therewith finiſhed the temple of Appollo, after that they deuiſed to make a temple to the goddeſse Diana, wherein they dyd deuiſe an other Symetrie, for that temple, as they hadde done for the temple of Appollo, and faſhioned it after the iuſte meaſure of a woman, to the ende and purpoſe, it ſhoulde be more beautifull and ſklender, making it eighte Diameters, in height, and called it Ionica, after their countrey, adding therunto in the ſtead of her ſhoowe, that which Vitruuius, nameth Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, and in the Capitel, was ſet Voluta, in the ſteade of her heare, whiche truſsed vp with a lace, on eyther ſide of her heade, for an ornature and garniſhment of the Capitell They alſo faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the body of the pilloure, and filled it with Canalicoli, and Striges, as thoughe it were the plates of her garmentes. Then they being more delighted with the beautifulnes of the height therof added alſo an other Diameter, vnto the forſaid Dorica, and made it ſeuen Diameters, in heght. After that in the citie of Corinthe, was buried a certaine maiden, after whoſe burial her nouriſhe (who lamented much her death) knowing her delightes to haue bene in pretye cuppes and ſuche like conceytes in her life time, with many other proper thinges appertayninge onely to the pleaſure of the eye, toke them, and brake them, and put them into a littell preatie baſkette, and did ſette the baſket on her graue, and couered the baſket with a ſquare pauinge ſtone. That done, with weping teares ſhe ſayde Let pleaſure go wyth pleaſure, and ſo the nouriſhe departed. It chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced that the baſket was ſet vpon a certain roote of an herbe called Acanthus, in frenche Branckurſine, or bearefote with vs, now in the ſpring time of the yere, when euery roote ſpreadeth fourth his leaues, in the encreaſing they did ronne vp by the ſides of the baſket, vntill they coulde ryſe no higher for the ſtone, that couered the baſket, whiche being ſquare and caſtinge hys ſowre corners ouer the ſydes of the rounde baſket, conſtrained the braunches of the herbe to draw downwardes againe with a ſertaine compaſse, and ſo grewe to the faſhion that Vitruuius, calleth Voluta. So is there alſo other ſmaller that come oute of the Caules, and ſtalkes, and are named in greeke Helices, and the baſket beynge hydden vnderneth wyth a multitude of leaues. In thys cytie one Calimachus, an excellent Architectur, paſsyng or goinge thereby, regardinge the beawtifull worke of nature, afterwardes vſing then the meaſures of the forſayde Pillours, makynge the pillour Ionycke, vpon the whiche pillor or Scapus thereof, he ſet the Capitell, the whiche he hadde ſene vpon the tombe of the mayden, the whiche garniſhed beatifully the whole pillor, whiche Capitell, was in height the thicknes of the pillor, and named it Corinthia, becauſe it was made in the cytie of Corinthe, by thandes of Calimachus, who for the excellence of that arte was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Catatechnos, and after that this worke growing more and more to perfection came to the Romaynes, and ſo through oute all Italie, and manye other places, yea, and was throughlye practiſed by them. Then the Tuſcanes, beginning to builde, hauing knowlaige of the pillor, whiche was firſte inuented by the Ionians, vpon the Symetrie, of a ſtrong manne inuented to buylde ſtronglye after the maner aforſayde, yea, and to garniſhe alſo theyr cyties and townes beautifullye with a pillour of their owne deuiſe whyche yet at
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:1835:6"/> this preſent time, remayneth wholle in the citie of Forence and in the countreis there about they fourmed and faſhioned that pillor, whyche to thys daye is named after the ſayde countrey Tuſcana. The Romains, then wel practiſed in their meaſures of all the reſt of their Columes, and alſo deſirous to encreace ſo noble an arte, by ſome noble acceſsion, beholdyng and regardinge the beautifulnes of theſe foreſayd pillors, that is to ſay. Tuſcana, Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia, gathered oute of eche of the ſame pillers, that, whyche they thought moſte faire, and made a piller of pleaſure or triumphe, after the moſte excellent maner that euer was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This piller was firſte buylded to his perfection in the time of Titus, Veſpaſianus, who ſette it at hys triumphe in the higheſte place of hys arche triumphall, and called it Compoſita, or as ſome doo name her Italica. Theſe pillers, partelye for their beautye and comlines, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telye for their fortitude and ſtrength, the writers of them, haue reſembled and lykned to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain feyned Goddes and Goddeſses. As namely Tuſcana, is applied vnto Atlas, the kynge of Mauritania: Dorica, vnto Hercules and the god Mars: Ionica to Diana, or Appollo. Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia vnto Veſta or ſome lyke virgin, and Compoſita, to Pandora, of Heſiodus, the which he faineth to haue ben endewed wyth diuers of thoſe graces and coninge, wherwith the beforena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Goddes and Goddeſses were indewed, ſo that it ſemeth by the auncient writers and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, which haue made reherſall of theſe thinges, that they haue bene had in great eſtimation and priſe, as ye maye wel parceyue by Yſis, whiche buylded a temple in Egipte for her father Iupiter, bycauſe her huſbande Oſiris, and ſhe were in great eſtimation, and alſo for theyr beautifull inuentions and wyſedome, were honored as goddes. This maye well be gathered by their pillers and ornamentes, that belong therunto, the whyche were noted and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with He brewe letters, and alſo by the Sepulcres of Amaſis, whych was made more, then. M. D yeres before the birthe of Chriſte, in the whiche one of the Pyramides was CCClx. thouſande mens workes, the ſpace of twentye yeares, the whyche remayneth in Egipte to be ſene at this preſent daye, and manye other beautifull buildinges of that nacion. Reade. Diado. Sic. li. <hi>1.2.</hi> Alſo it ſemeth by many other writers, that after Babell decaied, incontinently the Hebrues moſt triumphantlye floriſhed in thys pointe. Thus we maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that the Hebrues, receyued their knowlage of the Babilonians, and the Grekes, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued it of the Hebrues, in lyke caſe the Latines, and the Italians receiued their, from the Grekes, the whyche our Author Vitruuius, doth not deny, in makynge demonſtrations to a Latine worke with Greke letters as vpon the inuention of the Grekes, whych concerninge hys ſcience in Architectura, in the whyche thing Vitruuius, ſemeth muche to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, as one, that did not diſdayne to acknowledge the authors and writers, out of whom he receiued his knowledge. In ſo muche, as in hys ſeuenthe booke of Architecture, he affirmeth (by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the notableſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that they which haue left theſe thinges in wryting, are to be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, whoſe names alſo I thought not altogyther the meteſt to be omitted, &amp; therfore do rebers theſe. Theodorus, which wrot of the Dorica. Eteſiphon and Metageues, who wrote of the Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica, which was ſet in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Diana, at Epheſis. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hermogenes, hath writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Diana in Magneſia, after Argelius, which made the reherſal of the Corinthes. Fiſtly Sathirus, &amp; Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus, who did ſpeake of Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolea, in Halicarnaſso, laſt both Cares, Briaxes, Scopas, Praxite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les &amp; many other, as Nexaria, Theoſides, Philemon, Demophilos, Pollis, Leonides. Silamon, Mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pus, Sarnacus, Euphranor, al the which verly, are to be thanked &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended throughly
<pb facs="tcp:1835:7"/> For by them we know and perceiue (as thoughe we ſawe in a loking glaſse) the thinges, that haue bene ſene, done and made long before. Neuertheles, it hath ben withdrawen and hidden (as almoſt al other knowlages, for a long ſeaſon hath hene) through ignoraunce, for ſo it came to paſse by the iniurie of time, that all ſciences and learning haue bene kept ſecret and not ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, in ſo much that at this daye, there are many which name this order of building to be of the new facion. But it can not he new, that hath ſo many ancient Authors and maiſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, whom, namely the Noble writer or Author Pliny, hath in ſo great eſtimation, that for their ſake he blameth al them greatly, that haue written and wrought any thing, and haue not named the authors and maiſters, of whom they toke their inuention eſpecially of ſuche great and vnſpeakable worke, of which the honour and fame, hath bene aſmuch vnto the maker ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, as it was vnto them that cauſed thoſe thinges to be made. But now of thie thinges we haue ſpoken ynough, let vs therfore ſpeake ſome what of the worthynes of this ſcience, and of the office of an Architect.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>VVhat the Office and Duetie is of him that vvyll be a Perfecte Architecte or Mayſter of buyldings.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rchitectur (by the common conſent of many notable men) as Ceſarius ſayth, ys of all artes, the moſt noble and excellent, Contayning in it ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie ſciences and knowlaiges wherwyth it is furniſhed and adourned, as full well Vitruuius doth affyrme and declare by his writinge. For ſaith he, an Architecte muſt be ſharpe of vnderſtandinge and both quicke and apte to conceiue the trewe Inſtructions and meaninges of them that haue written therof: and muſt alſo be a perfect diſtributor of the great miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, that he hath perceued and experymented, that playnlye and briefly he maye diſcuſse and open demonſtrations of that which ſhalbe done or mete to thoſe perſones, that ſhalbe the fown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of any noble workes wherfore he ought firſt to be a very good Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marian, then to haue experte knowladg in drawing and protracting the thinge, which he hath conceyued, Nexte he muſt haue a good ſight in Geometrie, Conſequently in Opticke and in ſuche lyke ſciences he muſt haue good perceuerance. Likewiſe in Arithmeticke he muſt be very parfiact, and in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſingulerly well ſeene. He muſt alſo haue a good ſighte in Muſycke, and ſome knowlaige in Phiſicke, not altogether ignoraunt in Aſtronomie, he muſt alſo beſides all thiſe ben Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, very experte. The cauſes why al thiſe ſciences before named, ought to be in him that is a parfaict Architect and maiſter of buildinges be of Vitruuius in this ſorte reherſed. If he haue (ſaith he) learninge he ſhall ſtrengthen his memory, with all written bookes, and throughe drawing vtter his fantaſie and ſhewe the trike or faſcion of the thing that he goeth about to make And Geometrie teacheth vs the order of rules, Compaſses, Squiers, Quadran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and Iuſte waterleueles with manie other knowlaiges that procedeth thereof as Euclide, and other authours &amp; alſo Sebaſtian Serli, in his firſt Chapiter reherſeth, Opticke ſheweth vs howe and by what meanes the lightes ſhould be ſet into the Houſe, And howe they ſhould be brought from place to place, as to ſerue the hole houſe, and euery place therin, whiche Optica, is properly called perſpectiue, and is of a furder ſpeculacion, then therin can or nedeth to be expreſt: which of Sebaſtian Serlius, in his ſecond booke firſt ſecond and thirde Chapiter is
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:1835:7"/> partely declared. Arithmeticke, teacheth vs innumerable poinctes moſt neceſsarily required to the parfaicte knowlaige of this art<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for without yt, we can neither know or yet diſcuſse the meaſures and harde ſentences or queſtions of Symetrie, neither howe to accompte the Coſte and charges of our labores. An Architecte alſo muſt haue a knowlaige in hyſtories, There be moreouer multitude of cauſes in buildinges, and very many ornatures and garniſhinges of which he muſt nedes geue anſwere, from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they come, and for what purpoſe they are made, As for an example, If a maiſter workman ſhould make ymages, figured like women, clothed and garniſhed after a beautifull ſoarte, which are named Cariatides, and ſet them in his worke for pillers and make ouer their heade Mutilos, and Coronas, yf yt were demaunded of him to what purpoſe thoſe ymages wer made, then be ſhuld anſwer that Caria, a towne in Peloponeſo, trayterouſly conſpired with the Perſians, againſt the Grekes: But the grekes getting the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie ouer their enemies, agreed with one accord, and beſieged Caria, and wan the citie, killed the men and toke the women, carieng them as bond women not ſuffering them to put of their Ryche ornamentes and Iewelles to the intent, that the ſhowe of their triumphe, myght be thereby the more glorious. So they ſubdued, weare brought into bondage. For this cauſe and other ſuche lyke, the chief maiſters of Architecture made in their common places and pallaces ſuche women to beare vp the burthen of their buildinges, the whiche was a remembraunce and memorial of their puniſhmentes for their mallice againſt the Grekes, ſuſtained by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riatides, that is to ſaye, by the women of Caria. In lyke caſe dyd the Lacedemonians, whan they with ſo littell a power ouercame ſuche a great hoſt of the Percians, and ſlew them. After which conqueſt in their triumphe, they builded a gallery whiche ſhoulde remayne vnto them for a perpetuall and euerlaſting token of victorie and did ſet therin the figures, and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feites of the Percians, which before wer their priſoners, in their ſtraung apparaill, ſtanding in their pallaces, ſupporting their galleries, wherfore they were feared of their enemyes therby, and alſo yet encouraged the hartes of the Citizens, againſt their other enemies and backe fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Vpon this example Pauſanias, did afterwarde make the counterfeates of the ſame Perſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and vpon their heddes, he laide Epiſtilia, and Coronas, ſetting betwixt them Zophorus, the which was garniſhed and figured with the Ieweles, that they had taken from them being their enemies, As Cuppes, gobletes, cheines, girdelles, &amp; ſuche lyke other Iewelles, which wer plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full among the Perſians, and vnder their fete was ſet Stylobata, wherin were written their titles, Many ſuche Hiſtories an Architecte, ought of neceſsitye to know. Next vnto this doth follow Muſicke, which alſo is verie neceſsary for an Architecte, for theſe cauſes muſt he haue, as it were a foreſight in it, that therby the principall chambers of the houſe, ſhuld with ſuche order be made, that the voice or noyſe of muſicall Inſtrumentes, ſhould haue their perfaict Echo, reſounding pleaſauntly to the eares of thoſe that ſhalbe heares therof, as alſo the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, vſed in all their pallaces &amp; for many other neceſsities therunto belonging, of the which Vitruuius, maketh further demonſtration, as the refreſhing of the Melancolicke mindes, which ar alwaies trauailing for further knowlaige. But now conſequently followeth the cauſe why he ſhould haue ſight in Phiſicke, which through the knowlege of Aſtronomie, parfaictly doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the mouings of the heauens, and where vnto by their naturall inclinations they be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as alſo the vnderſtanding of the plages or Coaſtes of the word, which the Grekes call Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, to thyntent that he maye ſhewe what ground plottes ſtande in the moſt bolſom ayer to builde vpon. And which alſo be the ſwet and holſome waters, the moſte fertill and frutefull
<pb facs="tcp:1835:8"/> places, as namely for thoſe plottes that ſtand co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to thys order are not mete or neceſsarie to build vpon. This bolſome ground ſo found wheron Ye ſhall build, yemuſt furſt haue knowlaige how to caſt your ground plotte, wherin you muſt deuide all your ſeuerall places of offices ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partayning to the furniture of your houſe, your principall chambers of reſt and libraries, and ſuch other like muſt receyue their lightes from the Eaſt, for that the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by natural heate at his riſing draweth to him all corupte humors and euill vapors of the earth and quickneth the ſpirittes of man and beaſt, and if ye will caſt therin baynes or hot houſes, with winter Cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and parlors they ſhal receiue light from the weſt. For that ſide is defendid from the ſouth windes which are greuous and contagious and alſo great waſters of all kinde of buildinges, as may welbe parceuyd by old Edifices. Your ſtudy places, were you wold write, draw or deuiſe, or the places wher your Sellers ſhuld be caſt, ought to receiue their light from the northe, by cauſe in that parte are the lights, which are ſtedfaſt, As for lights other wayes appointed I referre to the builders of thoſe works. But Vitruuius, maketh no further mention therof. Now alſo it belongeth to an Architecte, to haue the knowlaige of Aſtronomie, wherby he ſhould directly know the foure principal places, which are Eaſt, weſt, north, and ſouth, with that, whiche they call Equinoctium, and Solſticium, and the mouings of the ſterres, for without this knowlaige none can attaine vnto the making of horologes, quadrantes, Clockes dialles, in the ſonne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary to be ſet in goodly Edyficies. It belongeth alſo to an Architect, to haue ſight in Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, which teaching to be of a noble courage as Vitruuius ſaith, and alſo gentil, curtious, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and modeſt, not geuen to auarice and filthy lucre, as not to be troubled or corrupted with rewardes or giftes, but with grauity and Sagenes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceine al honor and dignity in al thinges conſeruinge his good name and eſtimation. Let him alſo take a charge of workes in hand, being deſired and not deſirous of workes. He, which wold be an expert Architecte, ought to haue all theſe ſciences and knowlaiges, To him that hath any ſcience or knowlaige and iudgment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with conceiued, it is moſt euident and plaine. Neuertheleſse it will ſound ſtraungely to ſome that a man ſhoulde learne ſo many ſciences for the atteining of one, and kepe all them in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie for the practiſe of the ſame: yet it is neceſsary and alſo mete, that although he be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faict in them or euery of them, yet he ſhould haue ſome knowlaig in them and ſo it behoueth, neither it is requiſit that he ſhould be ſo parfaict a Gramaria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as was Ariſtarchus, and yet not altogether with out it. Nor in Muſicke like vnto Ariſtoxenis, neither in painting like Apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les nor Plaſtes, or Stattuary like vnto Miron or Policrates, neither in Phiſike like to Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, but yet in this and other not altogether ignoraunt. But yf à man myght be parfaict in al theſe ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces as were Ariſtarchus, Samrius, Plulolaus, Architas, Tarentinus, Apollonius, Pergeus, Eratoſthenes, Sireneus, Archimedes, Scopinas, (for all theſe were ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gely weapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with al theſe ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces before reherſed) he ſhould be able to anſwer to all queſtiones therto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining. But I may pray as Vitruuius doth, ſaying, I pray O Caeſar, and all other that rede this my writinges, if ther be any thing diſagreing to any of theſe ſciences beare with me for I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſse my ſelfe (ſaith he) not to be parfaict in any of the other ſciences. But he nameth him ſelfe to be an Architect, wherein he thinketh him ſelfe parfait, But I the ſetter forth of this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe in Engliſhe, acknolage myſelf not to be a parfaict Architecte, (as he ſaith) nor yet Grama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; though I haue put my ſelfe in preaſe, it is not through the depe knowlaige aboue reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but I do it for to put in vre an entrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or beginning to them which be therin Ignoraunt, &amp; deſyre further knowledge in theſe thinges, as hereafter appereth by the declaration hereof.</p>
               <pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:1835:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:9"/>
               <pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:1835:9"/>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram and illustration of Tuscan column</figDesc>
                     <head>THVSCANA.</head>
                  </figure>TVSCANA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He maner and forme of the fiue principall pillors, and their proper names with all their compoundes therto belonging and, their ſetting in their iuſt places by the order and rule of Symetria, and marked with the letters A. B. C. wherunto is made this piller Tuſcana, as it is figured, inuented and made by the Ionians, vpon the Simetrie of a ſtrong man. Renewed and found agayne by the Tuſcanes and o them taketh his name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> THVSCANA.</hi>
               </p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:10"/>
               <p>whoſe marke is K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Proiecture or ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging ouer ſhalbe ſo muche as the pillor is diminiſhed on eche ſide, the which is correſpondent to the thicknes of Scapus beneth. Thus writeth Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Serlias, of the proiecture of this Capitall. Neuertheles I haue ſene in ſome places in Italie that the Proiecture, haue bene like to their height, by cauſe the pillor is ſo muche dyminiſhed it ſhould be therefore the more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mely to haue the greater Proiecture, and yet ſhall thoſe two wayes not differ muche one from the other. But yet of theſe two wayes let vs take the moſte faire I haue alſo ſene this pillor ſo placed that it hath bene. <hi>7</hi> Dyameters in heigthe, where as he ſupported no other pillors but his owne Trabiacions. So endeth the forme and meaſures of the Capitulum.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EPISTILIVM.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the Capitall ſhalbe layde or ſet Epiſtilium, named alſo Trabes called in oure Engliſh tonge the Architraue the which is marked with Land is a modulus in height. The which height ye ſhal deuide into <hi>6.</hi> parts wherof Tenia, to be the ſixte part, &amp; the other <hi>.5</hi> partes is for Trabs. So done: vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Epiſtilium you ſhal ſet Zophorus being alſo a Modulus, in height and is marked with M. vppon Zophorus, ſhalbe ſet Coronix being in height alſo a Modulus, &amp; that height you ſhall deuid into <hi>.4</hi> partes geue one part vnto Cimatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder Corona marked with N. but the other ſide of it is called Tenia, and geue likwiſe <hi>2</hi> parte vnto Corona marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> O. &amp; the fourth part which remaineth geue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cymatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer Corona which is marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> P. In Corona, ye ſhal make Denticulos, the which are made like teethe and their Proiectures, ſhalbe like vnto their heightes, ſauing only Corona which hangeth his height and halfe his height ouer. And thus endeth the meſures of the pillor called Tuſcana. Now ye ſhal vnderſtand, that the pillor which ſtandeth in the myddell is your ground plotte, but the other whiche ſtandeth by him, is made vpon the ſelf ſame meaſure but that it is otherwiſe garniſhed whiche garniſhmentes bring other meaſures for them. And as touching this pillor, I ſhall begin from the loweſt parte of the Pedeſtall being Tenia inferior, deuiding his height into <hi>.8.</hi> partes. Geue <hi>.3.</hi> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes vnto Plinthus &amp; <hi>.4.</hi> partes geue alſo to Sima reuerſa, and the eighte parte remaineth for the ſmall edge vpon Sima. vpon the whiche is ſette the bodye of the Pedeſtale, alſo the vpper Tenia ye ſhall deuide his height into <hi>5</hi> partes geue. <hi>2</hi> partes vnto Hypotrachelium, and alſo <hi>.2.</hi> partes vnto Cymatium, and the fift. part geue vnto his edge at the toppe of the Pedeſtale, nowe Baſis, or Baſe, belonging to the ſayde pillor is the height of a Modulus, or half the thicknes of the pillor, whoſe height ye ſhall deuide into <hi>.2.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Geue Plinthus one parte, and the ſecond part deuide you into <hi>.3.</hi> partes Geue <hi>.2.</hi> partes vnto Torus, and the third part deuide alſo into <hi>.3.</hi> partes. Geue <hi>.2.</hi> partes to Sima and the third parte ye ſhall geue the edge vnder Sima So endeth the meſures of the Baſis or Baſe, vpon the which Baſe ſhalbe ſet Scapus, or the body of the pillor, made after the maner &amp; order as before is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the which ſhalbe ſet the Capital the one Capital, is like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſauing that it hath vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Echinus a littel edge, which ſeteth forth Plinthus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a more beautiful Proiecture. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Architraue or Epiſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, as before reherced a Modulus in height, which height ye ſhal deuide into <hi>.6.</hi> partes. Tenia, occupieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſixt part, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other <hi>.5.</hi> partes ye ſhal deuid into <hi>.2.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Geue one part vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> half of Trochilus, the other part is left for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> flat ſquare, that reſteth vpon the Capital &amp; ſo endeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Epiſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now as touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fries or Zophorus, being alſo a Modulus in height, as is before reherſed of the other, is like vnto it but that this ſwellet houte
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:1835:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:1835:11"/> the fourth part of a round compas, that is drawen aboue &amp; ſquare being the height and bredth of a modulus wherwith endeth Zophorus, vpon the whiche ſhalbe ſette Coronix, the one ſide is like vnto the other in the meſures, but that in this ſide Cymatium, is ſet vnder Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and vpon the other ſide Tenia is ſet vnder Corona, being of one heighte. This done and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed according to this rule ſo endeth the meſures and garniſhmente of the firſt piller called Tuſcana.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe for as moche as that you haue vnderſtanding bowe all the partes of this piller &amp; the reſt of the pillors that ſhalbe, hath theyr meſures, ornatures, and names finiſhed out of Icnographia or ground plot vpwardes to the very top of the ſame worke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought it good for the more perfection and exerciſes of the genteſt reader to make a Reherſall of all the partes and paſselles downwardes agayne endyng in Ichnogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia where I began firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> theſe be the names TRABEATIONIS. Cymatium, mar. P. Corona, mar. O. Tenia. mar. N. Zophorus, mar. M. Tenia in Epiſtylium, mar. L. CAPITVLI. Plinthus mar. K. Echinus, Et Annullus mar. I, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potrachelium mar. H. COLVMNA mar. F. Aſtragalus marked. G, Apophiges ſuperior &amp; inferior, SPIRA ſine BASIS. Torus mar. E. Plinthus mar. D. STYLOBATAE. Tenia pro Coronice mar. C. Tenia pro Baſis mar. B. Ichnogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia mar. A. being the parfecte ſquare or ground plot the beginning and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion of this worke.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1835:11"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram and illustration of Doric (?) column</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:1835:11"/>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> DORICA.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:12"/>
               <head>HERE FOLOVVETH THE MANER AND FORME of the ſecond pillor called Dorica, being aſcribed to Hercules and Mars, for his ſtrength, accordinge to the rule aforeſayde.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His pillor called Dorica, ſhalbe <hi>.7.</hi> Diameters in height, with the Baſe, and Capitall Now if ye will ſet Stylobata, or Pedeſtal, vnder your pillor, thus ye ſhal begin. Firſt you ſhall make a foure ſquare, which ſhalbe your grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, the which is in my figure marked with A. and then draw a lyne ouerthwart from the one corner to the other, which line is called Dyagonalis, and is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with B. and that lyne being directly vpright ſet, one ende ſhalbe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> height of the ſquare or body of the Pedeſtall marked with C. meaſure and deuide that height into <hi>5.</hi> partes the which height of the Baſe of the Pedeſtall, ſhalbe as muche, as one of the <hi>.5.</hi> partes whiche is marked with D. and admitte alſo aſmuche vnto the Coronix of the Pedeſtalle marked with E. ſo that the Pedeſtale is <hi>.7.</hi> ſuche partes in height like vnto the pillor, which is <hi>7.</hi> Dyameters, in height. The height of the Baſis of the Pedeſtale which is marked with D. ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.2.</hi> partes the loweſt part is for Plinthus, marked with F. the ſecond part deuide into <hi>.5.</hi> partes. Three of thoſe partes geue vnto Torus, marked with G. the other <hi>.2.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.3.</hi> partes, geue <hi>.2.</hi> partes vnto Aſtragalus, marked with H. the third parte is lefte for the edge which Vitruuius calleth Regula, the Proiecture, of eche ſide of the Baſe, of the Pedeſtall as Vitruuius ſaieth ſhalbe halfe a Modulus, but the antiques haue made their Proiectures like vnto their heightes. Then deuide the height of Coronix marked with E into <hi>.3.</hi> partes geue one vnto Aſtragalus, with his Regula, marked with I. the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> partes admiting <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe partes to Cymatium, marked with K. and the thirde parte thereof is lefte for Regula, whoſe marke is L. the Proiectures of the ſame is like vnto their heightes. Thus endeth the Pedeſtale or Stylobata.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SPIRA SIVE BASIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the Pedeſtale, you ſhall ſet Spiram which is the fote or Baſe of the pillor and is marked with M. being a Modulus in height. that height deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> partes one of thoſe partes is for Plinthus marked with N. the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes deuide into. <hi>4.</hi> partes. one of them ſhalbe for Torus, aboue marked with O. The other <hi>.3.</hi> partes that remayneth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide into <hi>2</hi> partes, one of them geue vnto Torus, vnder marked with P. the reſt is admitted vnto Trochitus, marked with Q. and eache of his rules to be either of them in height the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth part of that hole meaſure or parte. The Proiectures of the whole Baſis, ſhalbe half a Modulus, on eche ſide, and thus endeth the meſures of the Baſis.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SCAPVS SIVE COLVMNA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon Spira, or Baſe of the pillor ye ſhal ſet Scapus, marked with R. being the tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nike or body of the pillor the which is in height <hi>.6.</hi> Diameters. The thicknes of the pil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lor at the foote is deuided into <hi>.6.</hi> partes: and vnder the Capital, it is diminiſhed one of the <hi>.6.</hi> partes that is half a parte on eyther ſide, and the <hi>.5.</hi> partes which remaigne,
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:1835:12"/> be for the thicknes of the pillor vnder the Capitale. From the whiche thicknes ye ſhall drawe downe perpendiculerly vnto the third part of the height of Scapus, whervpon is made the halfe compas the which <hi>.2.</hi> lynes ſhal make <hi>.2.</hi> croſses on eche ſide of the half compas one. Then meſure from the croſse by the ſide of the halfe compas vnto the loweſt part of the half compas and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the ſame into <hi>.6.</hi> partes, drawinge them ouerthwarte the halfe compas from the one ſide of the pillor vnto the other marking the endes of the lynes with <hi>.1.2.3.4.5.6.</hi> then meaſure from the ouerthwarte lyne vnder the halfe compas, deuiding vpwardes to the higheſt of Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus into <hi>.6.</hi> partes The which ſhalbe drawne ouerthwarte the pillor, the higheſt ouerthwarte line at the toppe of Scapus, marking that lyne with <hi>1.</hi> on and ſo the other downewardes with <hi>2.3.4.5.6.</hi> Then the ſtrike marked with <hi>.1.</hi> one vnder the Capitall, is drawen downe on bothe the ſides vnto the lyne that ledeth to the half compas, whiche is alſo marked with one. Then drawe downe righte from the ſtrike <hi>.2.</hi> whiche is drawin ouerthwarte the pillor at the toppe vnto the other lyne, which leadeth to the half compas <hi>.2.</hi> and ſo downwardes from <hi>.3.</hi> perpendy culerly to the other lyne or croſse marked with <hi>.3.</hi> and ſo directly downwardes from <hi>.4.</hi> to <hi>.4.</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>5.</hi> to <hi>.5.</hi> and ſo likwiſe from. <hi>6.</hi> to. <hi>6.</hi> That done, take a rule, and drawe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>2.</hi> ſtrikes which are the thicknes of the pillor vnder the Capitall to the end of the vpright line marked <hi>.2.</hi> which ſtayeth that lyne which is drawen ouerthwart the pillor marked alſo <hi>.2</hi> and drawe from <hi>.2.</hi> to the end of the vpright lyne marked <hi>.3.</hi> and ſo likwiſe from <hi>.3.</hi> to <hi>.4.</hi> downewardes: and ſo from <hi>.4.</hi> to <hi>.5.</hi> and from <hi>.5</hi> to <hi>.6.</hi> So done, ye haue cloſed vp the ſides with the diminiſhinge of your pillor as ye may perceiue by your grounde plot, the other ſide is lefte vncloſed, wherin ye may perceue, where the lynes do ſtoppe, whiche be drawne vpwardes out of the half compas. The other ſide of the pillor I haue cloſed becauſe ye ſhuld ſee it and the better vnderſtand therby how to cloſe and finiſh the diminiſhing of the pillors. At the toppe of Scapus, or Pillor, right vnder the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, is made Aſtragalus, with his Regula being in height the ſixte parte of Modulus. The which Regula, ſhalbe halfe ſo much in height as the height of Aſtragalus, marked with S. whoſe Proiectures, ſhalbe ſomuch as the pillor is diminiſhed on eche ſide a like. If your pillor ſhall haue Canaliculos, there muſt be of thoſe <hi>.20.</hi> round about Scapus, ſo done make a ſquare ſo greate, as one of thoſe <hi>.20.</hi> partes, then drawe from corner to corner ouerthwart the ſquare, makyng a croſse in the mydell of that ſquare. Then take a payre of compaſses and ſet the one ende of your compaſses in the middell of the croſſe, and draw with the other poincte of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſses al a long by the ſide of your ſquare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one corner to the other, compaſsing the ſame quarter as more plainely doth appere by your ground plot marked with A. the whiche ar the right Canalicoli, Beneth at the foote of Scapus, lieth Regula, being of the ſame height that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtragalus is of at the toppe, and ſo endeth Scapus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CAPITAL.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Ppon the toppe of Scapus, you ſhall ſet the Capitall or hedde of the pillor marked with T. and is in heigth a iuſt Modulus, that height deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> partes Geue one part vnto Hypotrachelium marked with V. and the ſecond part deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe ſhalbe for Echinus, marked with .X. the reſt is lefte for the <hi>.3.</hi> kinges which be called Apophiges, or. Anuli, Now the thirde and higheſte parte, deuyde you alſo into <hi>.3</hi> partes wherof <hi>.2</hi> of thoſe partes ſhalbe geuen to Plinthus marked with. Y. the thirde parte,
<pb facs="tcp:1835:13"/> whiche remaineth, geue to Cymatium, and his rule or Regula, which Regula, ſhalbe the thirde parte of that, which remaineth and lieth at the toppe of the Capitale. The Proiecture of this Capitale, ſhalbe correſpondent with the proiecture of the Plinthus, at the foote of the pillor, and is marked with N the whiche Proiecture, is obſerued of the Antiques, in the ſayd pillor, which is already finiſhed and ſtandeth by. Howbeit Vitruuius writeth it to be made after this ſorte, to wit, that the Proiecture of the Capitale ſhalbe the twelueth and ſixte parte of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulus. Thus is finiſhed the Capitale with all his Proiectures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EPISTYLIVM.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the Capitale, ſhalbe ſet Epiſtylium marked with A. the height therof ſhalbe a Modulus that height ye ſhall deuide into. <hi>7.</hi> partes. Geue Tenia, marked with B. the ſeuenth parte, and geue Subtenia, and Gutta, pendante marked with C. the ſixte part of a modulus to their height and that part deuide vnto <hi>.4.</hi> partes, Geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto Gutta pendant being <hi>.6.</hi> in number, the fourth part ſhall be for the edge or Regula, in Epiſtylia vnder Tenia.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ZOPHORVS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon Epiſtylium, ſhalbe ſet Triglyphi, marked with D. whoſe height muſte be a Modulus and a halfe. Alſo the bredth therof ſhalbe a Modulus, and that bredth you ſhall deuide into <hi>.12.</hi> partes Geue <hi>1.</hi> of thoſe. vnto eche one of the Semicanalicoli, the which ſtand on either ſyde of the Triclyphi, ſo remayne yet <hi>.10.</hi> partes and <hi>.6.</hi> of thoſe ſhalbe for Strie, or the flath whiche are marked with E. the other <hi>4</hi> partes are left for the Canalicoli, ſtanding vpright with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Triglyphi, wher vpon ye ſhall ſet his Capitale, which alſo is called Tenia, being in height the ſixte part of. Modulus and marked with F. Bitwixte the <hi>.2.</hi> Triglyphos, yow ſhall ſet Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thopa, marked with G. being ſquare ſo high as it is broad: and in that ſquare ſhalbe made a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les bed, his hornes bound about with rybandes: garniſhed with branches flowers and Iewelles, hanging at the endes of the Ribandes In euery ſecond Methopa, ought to be made a faire baſone or flat peace, the which inwardely: ſhuld be garniſhed but I am not hable to ſet fourth the bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye therof in ſo ſmall a figure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The higheſt parte of TRABEATIONIS, called in Engliſh a Corniſhe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Itruuius teacheth vs that the height of it ſhuld be a Modulus, and that yow ſhall deuide into <hi>2.</hi> partes the loweſt parte deuide into <hi>.5.</hi> partes, Geue <hi>.1.</hi> to Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matium vnder Corona alſo <hi>.1.</hi> other vnto Cymatium, aboue Corona, the other <hi>.3</hi> partes geue vnto Corona, whoſe marke is H, that ſecond parte which remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of the Modulus ye ſhall geue vnto Syma, marked with I. Then adde the eight part of a Modulus, to be the height for his edge or Regula, aboue Sima the proiectures to be like to their heightes, ſauing that the Proiecture of Corona, muſt be twiſe his height by cauſe in it muſt be made, the order of Gutta, being right ouer Triglyphi, they ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be,
<pb facs="tcp:1835:13"/>
                     <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:1835:14"/> 
                     <hi>.18.</hi> in nomber <hi>.6.</hi> the one way and <hi>.3.</hi> the other. Right ouer Methopa, the Antiques vſed to cut in Corona Iupiters mark of the thunder bolte. Thus endeth the opinion of Vitruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ius in theſe thinges. Neuertheles as ye may perſeue by the muller or Coronicis, of the antiques that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth on the right ſide wherunto they haue added Echinus, and Denticuli, with Apophigis or rule &amp; garniſhed it after many beautiful facions bringing their worke to a great height, the which height cauſeth a fairer Proiecture, which was for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> further ſetting fourth of their work<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; was pleaſant to the beholders therof. If it be a gate houſe or gallery of pleaſure hauing Ionica, or Corinthia, of him ſupported or ſtanding by him: then ought he to be richly garniſhed But if he ſtande in the gate of a citie or caſtel by force or ſtrength, then ought he to be made with thoſe ſtrong meaſures, which are aſcribed vnto him ſtanding in the place of Mars, &amp; Hercules wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſtandeth with the other pillors he is like vnto Minerua, and therfore haue reſpecte vnto his place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus hauinge finiſhed all the meaſures ending now at the higheſt of TRABEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIONIS. I ſhall name al the partes and parſsels with their markes whereby is knowen the thing that is wrighten or ſpoken of to the clearnes or opening of matters, and an excerciſe for the reader to know the names by, I haue more at large ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ending of the Tuſcan piller, therfore I ſhall begine in TRABEATIONIS: REGVLA. &amp; Sima, marked with I. Cymatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Corona, marked with H. Cymatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inferior (Echinus Regula, Denticulos) added Tenia, marked with F. Triglyphi, marked with D. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thopa, marked with G. Tenia, marked with B. Regula and Gutta, marked with C. CAPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVLI, marked with T. Regula Cymatium Plinthus, marked with Y. Echinus marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> X. Annulitres. Hipotrachelium, marked with V. COLVMNA or SCAPVS. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiges Superior &amp; Apophiges inferior, marked with R. SPIRA or BASIS, marked with M. Torus ſuperior, marked with O. Regula. Scotia, marked with Q. Regula Torus Inferior, marked with P. Plinthus, marked with N. STYLOBATA. Coronix marked E. Regula, marked with L. Cymatium, marked with K. Aſtragalus, marked with I. to the antike pillor is added Corona, Regula, and Sima, Quadratum, Diagonium, marked with C. the diagonall line marked B. Ichnographia, or ground plot marked with A. BASIS, marked with D. Regula, Aſtragalus, marked with H. Torus, marked G. Plinthus marked F. in the finiſhed pillor or BASIS, is as followeth Regula Cymatium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſa. Regula Sima. Reuerſa Regula, Plinthus, which maketh an end for this piller.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1835:14"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram and illustration of Ionic column</figDesc>
                     <head>IONICA</head>
                  </figure>
                  <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:1835:14"/>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> IONICA.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:15"/>
               <head>THE MANER FORME AND ORDER of the Symetria, or meaſure of Ionica, whiche was deuiſed by the Ionians and ſet in the temple of Diana.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Tylobata, or Pedeſtale of Ionica, you ſhal make the boddy therof after this ſorte. The flat ſtone, which is marked with A. ſhalbe a ſquare and a halfe in height, and that height you ſhal deuide into <hi>.6.</hi> partes, &amp; adde therto ſuch an other part for the height of the Baſe of this Pedeſtale which is marked with B &amp; ſet alſo ſuch an other like part for the height of the Coronix of this Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtale marked with C. So done, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pedeſtale is <hi>.8.</hi> partes in height, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> height of the baſe marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> B. ye ſhal deuide into <hi>.5.</hi> parts. Geue <hi>.1.</hi> part vnto Aſtragalus &amp; his Regula, marked with D. the which Regula, occupieth the third parte of that one parte. Geue alſo to Sima reuerſa, with his edge marked with. E, one parte, wherof his Edge occupieth the third parte. Then ye ſhall geue an other parte vnto Torus, marked with F. and the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes you ſhall geue vnto Plinthus, marked with G. The Proiecture of them ſhalbe like vnto their heightes. Now the height of Coronix, marked with C. ye ſhal deuid into <hi>10.</hi> partes, wherof you ſhall geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto Cymatium, and his Edge marked with H. and alſo geue <hi>.3.</hi> partes vnto Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, marked with Land alſo geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto Syma, marked with K. the tenth parte is left, for the Aſtragalus &amp; his edge marked with L. The Proiectures be like vnto their heightes but that Corona, doth ſayle ouer twiſe his height. Thoughe this pillor and al other pillors if it were ſo that they had double Plinthus, it ſhould not be without good cauſe, for the antiques haue made three Plinthus, one aboue an other, the occaſion wherof is this, that the earthe ſhould not ouer growe the Baſe of the Pedeſtale, and ſo hyde the chief thinge wherupon do reſte the whole or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denaunces yea and in many other places, they are neceſsary the which al Architectes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of buildinges ought to knowe, and many moo of thoſe and ſuch other ought to be knowen of them of neceſsitie. The occaſion or cauſe for the whiche I haue begonne this order or rule, firſt with the Pedeſtale, (the which rule differeth from Vitruuius, for he beginneth firſt with the pillor, neuertheles they come to one purpoſe in the parfection) is for this, that firſte in my Pedeſtale, I haue drawen the ground plotte, whiche the Greekes call Ichnographia. For that ſame houſe or building cannot ſtande or endure whiche hath no good foundacion. So this is the foundation through the whiche we knowe and finde all the meaſures and vprightes belonging to the pillor. In it is alſo found the Trabiations, the height of the Pedeſtale, and the bredth ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, alſo the height of his Baſe and Coronices, and the Diameter and the thicknes of the pillor aboue vnder the Capitalle, and likewiſe the heighte of Spira, or Baſe of the pillor: and the height of Scapus, and alſo the height of his Capitale, with all the whole Proiectures, and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures whiche iſsueth oute of this Ichnographia. Now to come to the right vnderſtandinge of theſe meaſures before reherſed, ye ſhall beginne thus. The bredth of the ſquare, whiche is the bredthe of the Pedeſtale, marked with A. yow ſhall deuide into <hi>.11.</hi> partes wherof <hi>.8.</hi> ſhalbe the Diameter, or thicknes of the pillor the whiche pillor in height ſhalbe <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters, with the Baſe and Capitalle, the whiche heighte of the Capitale, occupieth the third part of the Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the Baſis marked with M. ſhalbe half the thicknes of the pillor in height, thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Vitruuius, in his third booke and third Chapiter.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:1835:15"/>
                  <head>BASIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Baſis, or fote of the pillor ſhalbe a Modulus in height: which is marked with M. that height you ſhal deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> partes, geue one part vnto Plinthus marked with. N that which remaineth deuide into <hi>.7.</hi> partes geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto Torus, marked with. .O. the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>.4.</hi> partes deuide into <hi>.16</hi> parts, geue Trochilus ſuperior with his Aſtragali, and rules <hi>.8.</hi> of thoſe partes, wherof Trochilus, occupieth <hi>.6</hi> partes, vnto the higheſt Aſtragalus, and his edge ſhalbe geuen a part and half a part, &amp; vnto the litle edge vnder Torus geue alſo half a part, which maketh vp the reſt of the <hi>.8.</hi> partes. The other <hi>.8.</hi> partes geue vnto Trochilus inferior, and deuide them alſo as is before reherſed. The Proiecture, of the Plinthus, muſt be the eighte and the ſixtenth part of the thicknes of the piller which is the ſailing out on eache ſide of the Baſe of the pillor and doth anſwer vnto the bredth of the body of the Pedeſtale, and is agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel with the forſaid grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d plot. The Antiques haue made alſo a baſe, which differeth not farre from the declaration of Vitruuius and after this facion they haue ordeined their Baſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> height therof to be a Modulus, and that height deuide into <hi>.2.</hi> partes, wherof geue Plinthus one part, as before is taught by Vitruuius. Then that, which remaineth deuide alſo into <hi>.3.</hi> partes, wherof the higheſt part ſhalbe geuen to Torus, the other <hi>.2</hi> parts which remaine, deuide either of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into <hi>.6.</hi> parts wherof the higheſt Aſtragalus &amp; his rule occupieth <hi>.1.</hi> part, the which rule is half the height of Aſtragalus, alſo the edge, that lieth vnder Torus ſhal be half a part in height, and that which remaineth is for Trochilus ſuperior, wherwith finiſheth the firſt <hi>.6.</hi> partes. Nowe geue alſo <hi>.1.</hi> part to the lower Aſtragalus, and his Edge The loweſt edge that ſtandeth vppon Plinthus ſhalbe in height half a part, the <hi>.4.</hi> partes and a half that remaine, ſhalbe leſt for the Trochilus inferior. The Proiecture of the Plinthus, is before reherſed, but becauſe this Torus is ſklenderer then that, the which Vitruuius ſpeaketh of, it bringeth a more bewtifulnes to the Proiecture, which can not be here expreſsed as any man of knowlaige will confeſse.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SCAPVS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the baſe you ſhal ſet Scapus, marked with R. being <hi>.7.</hi> Diameters in height and therto adding the ſixte part of the Diameter The which height of Scapus ye ſhall deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> partes vpon the third parte make halfe a compas, then deuide the thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the pillor beneth into <hi>.6.</hi> partes <hi>.5.</hi> of thoſe partes ſhalbe the thiknes of the pillor or Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, at the toppe, that is half a part diminiſhed, one either ſide of Scapus, from thence drawe downe right one both ſides vnto the third parte of the pillor vpon the which is made the halfe compas The whiche <hi>.2.</hi> lines maketh <hi>.2.</hi> croſses vppon the half compas, Then meaſure from the croſse downewardes euen a longe by the ſide of the halfe compas, that ſtandeth vpon the third parte of the pillor deuiding it into <hi>.6.</hi> partes and drawe theſe lines ouerthwart the halfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas and marke the vpper line with <hi>.1.</hi> and ſo marke downewardes the next with <hi>.2.</hi> and ſo with the reſte as followeth <hi>.3. 4. 5. 6.</hi> then deuide from the loweſt of the half compas vpwardes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the toppe of the pillor vnder the Capitall, alſo into <hi>.6.</hi> partes drawing them ouerthwarte the pillor and marke them alſo downewardes with <hi>.1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.</hi> or deuide it into ſo many parts, as you will, the moo, the better, &amp; the parfaicter you ſhall diminiſhe your pillor. Then ſhal ye begine after this maner &amp; draw fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrike <hi>.2.</hi> downwardes vnto the ſtrike &amp; croſse, which
<pb facs="tcp:1835:16"/> is drawen ouerthwarte the halfe compas, and is alſo marked with <hi>.2.</hi> and drawe alſo from the ſtrike <hi>.3.</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hath alſo a croſse made vpon the halfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas, drawing vpwardes vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrike marked with <hi>.3.</hi> the which is drawn ouerthwart the pillor aboue, &amp; ſo drawe from <hi>.4.</hi> to <hi>.4.</hi> from <hi>5.</hi> to <hi>.5.</hi> and from <hi>.6.</hi> to <hi>.6.</hi> The line vnder the Capitall, at the toppe of the pillor marked with <hi>.1.</hi> from thence drawe with a rule downewardes to the ende of the vprighte line, which ſtaieth at the ouerthwart line marked <hi>.2.</hi> cloſing vp the ſide of the pillor, and from <hi>.2.</hi> vnto <hi>3,</hi> downewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and alſo from <hi>.3.</hi> vnto <hi>4</hi> from <hi>.4.</hi> vnto <hi>.5.</hi> and from <hi>.5.</hi> vnto <hi>.6.</hi> Then is that ſide full finiſhed and made vpright. At the foote of Scapus, is a littell ſmall edge, ſtanding vppon Torus whoſe height ſhalbe the ninthe part of Modulus, wherof his Proiecture ſhalbe of like height. Alſo at the toppe of the pillor lieth Aſtragalus, and his fillet being half ſo high as the Aſtragalus, &amp; alſo aboue the Aſtragalus, is a littel Edge, the which belongeth to the Capital: The meaſure of his Aſtragalus, and his Edge, which belongeth vnto Scapus is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out be the litel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas, which is the eye of Voluta, whoſe marke is .X. if the pillor ſhalbe garniſhed with Canalicoli ther ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be in number <hi>.24.</hi> rounde about the pillor or Scapus, and euery of them deuide into <hi>.5.</hi> partes <hi>.4.</hi> of thoſe partes is the bredth of Canalicoli, and the fifth parte is for Striae, which are alſo called Femora. The ground plotte therof ſtandeth beſid the pillor which is marked with .S. wherin ye may ſee the maner or making of Canalicoli, being half a compas inwardes, the whiche, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth far from the order of Dorica, as it appereth by your ground plotte. Thus endeth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and making of Scapus, with his meſures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CAPITAL.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Irectly and right vpon the top of Scapus you ſhall ſet this Capitall following, whiche is marked with .T. being in height the third part of a Diameter, the bredth of the Aba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus marked with V is a Diameter, &amp; therto alſo adde, the eighteneth part of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter. That ſame part deuide into <hi>2.</hi> partes The which <hi>.2.</hi> partes ſhalbe ſet one parte on eyther ſide of the Abacus, the whiche ſhal aide the Proiectures: ſo done Abacus is the in bredthe <hi>.19.</hi> partes, then tel from the vttermoſt part of Abacus inwardes, one part and a halfe of thoſe <hi>.19.</hi> partes and there drawe a ſtrike downe right perpendiculerly, as ye maye perceue by your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure here expreſsed whiche on both ſides of the Capitall, hangeth a line with a plommett at eche ende. Then deuide the hanging line from the higheſt of the Abacus, downewardes into <hi>6.</hi> partes a and half of ſuche meaſure as is before reherſed, wherof the height of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Abacus is one &amp; a half, of the which remaineth yet <hi>.8.</hi> partes on the hanging line, the which partes ſhal ſerue for Voluta, marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> .X. &amp; thoſe parts ſhalbe thus deuided. Betwixt the Abacus &amp; the litell round Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas, ſhalbe <hi>.4.</hi> parts &amp; beneth the litel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas is <hi>.3.</hi> partes and the compas it ſelf is alſo <hi>.1.</hi> part. That part, which is the litell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas ye ſhal deuid his height into <hi>.6.</hi> parts Then take a paire of compaſses and ſet the one poincte of the compaſses in the toppe of the ſmall compas whiche I haue marked with <hi>.1.</hi> &amp; the other fote of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas ye ſhal ſet vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> line vnder the Abacus, &amp; then turne the compas aboute &amp; drawe downewardes vnto the loweſt of thoſe <hi>.8.</hi> partes belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to Voluta, vntil ye come to the line wher at the plomet doth hang and there ſtay with that poinct of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas, &amp; bring the other poinct of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas downe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loweſt ſtrike of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> litle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pas, which is marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>.2.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> turne vpwards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loweſt poinct of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas vntil ye come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging line, wher ye ſhal ſtay. The other fote ye ſhal ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrike marked <hi>.3.</hi> being within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> litle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsing about w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt part of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas downwards vntil ye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e again to the
<pb n="X" facs="tcp:1835:16"/> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging line and ſo remoue the higheſt part of the compas ſetting it on the ſtrike <hi>.4.</hi> within the litle compas, and drawe vpwardes with the other poincte of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas vntill ye come to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiculer line, ſtaing againe there, and then ſet the other foote of the compas right vppon the ſtrike marked with <hi>.5.</hi> alſo being within the litle compas, and drawe downe wardes againe vnto the forſayde line, and ſo ſet the higheſt poinct of the compas vppon the ſtrike marked with <hi>.6.</hi> being alſo within the litle compas. Then drawe with the other poinct of the compas vpwardes again which doth incloſe the litle compas. In the which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas may be made a roſe or ſome other flower. Then ſhall ye perceue that the Aſtragalus, and his <hi>.2.</hi> edges are Iuſte the height of the litle compas, which is the eye of Voluta, and then ſhall the height of Echinus be <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe parte that Voluta was made with, the whiche Echinus is marked with Y. alſo that ſpace that lieth betwen Echinus, &amp; Abacus ſhalbe <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe parts in height. So done ye haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trewe height &amp; bredthe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forfront &amp; face of the Capital. It is alſo nedefull to know how to forme &amp; facion the ſide of the Capitall, The maner &amp; facion therof ſtandeth betwixt the <hi>.2.</hi> pillers. The Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, that lieth vpon Voluta, is iuſt <hi>.4.</hi> ſquare flat like to a trencher, the Proiecture is as muche as one of the <hi>.19,</hi> partes on eche ſide of the Abacus, from the which ye ſhall draw downe the <hi>.2.</hi> ſides of Voluta, which is <hi>8.</hi> of thoſe partes, the <hi>.2.</hi> Edges that ſtand on eche ende of the Rolle or Voluta ſhal haue <hi>.1.</hi> part betwixt them both. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take a paire of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſse &amp; ſet the one poinct of the compas at the loweſt and inner parte of the litle edge marked with <hi>.1.</hi> and bring the other poinct of the compas into the innermoſt corner of the other edge whiche is marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>.2.</hi> drawe from thence downewardes to the figure <hi>3.</hi> then ſet the poinct againe in the place marked with <hi>.2.</hi> &amp; drawe with the other poinct of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas downe to this figure <hi>.3.</hi> againe, and it ſhall make a croſse, vppon that croſse, ſet the one poinct of the compas, &amp; with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other poinct of the compas draw from the ſtrike marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>.1.</hi> vnto the other ſtrike marked with <hi>.2.</hi> &amp; it wylle ſhew you the diminiſhing of Voluta in the middel, through which diminiſhing you ſhal perceue the endes of the Canaliculi. So done the ſide of the Capitall, is twiſe ſo broade as it is in height, the Proie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of Echinus, is like and equall with the Proiecture of Regula at the foote of Scapus, and ſo ende the Proiectures, and meſures of this Capitall alſo the. Antiques in diuers of their edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, hath made Echinus, to be in Proiecture like vnto Abacus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EPISTILIVM.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ver the Capital or hed of the piller ye ſhal ſet Epiſtilium, or Architraue whoſe marke is A. the height therof ſhalbe a Modulus, and that height ye ſhall deuide into <hi>.7.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, one of thoſe ye ſhall geue vnto Cymatium marked with B. his proiecture is like vnto his height. The other <hi>.6.</hi> partes ye ſhal deuide into <hi>.12.</hi> partes geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto the loweſt Faſcia marked with C geue <hi>.4.</hi> vnto the ſecond Faſcia marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> D. &amp; alſo geue vnto the third Faſcia the <hi>.5.</hi> partes which remaineth, the which is marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> E. whoſe Proiecture or hanging ouer ſhalbe right and Equall with the thicknes of the piller bynethe aboue the Baſe. Now vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that the Proiecture of theſe <hi>.2.</hi> higheſt Faſcias ſhalbe ſo muche as the piller is diminiſhed vpon the one ſide vnder the Capitall the which is the twelfthe part of the diameter, the which part you ſhall deuide into <hi>.9.</hi> partes, geue <hi>.5.</hi> vnto the higheſt Faſcia, marked with E. for his Proiecture, the other <hi>.4.</hi> partes ſhal ſerue for the Proiecture of the middle moſt Faſcia marked with D. the loweſt Faſcia, findeth his owne Proiecture as before is reherſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1835:17"/>
                  <head>ZOPHORVS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the Epiſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye ſhall ſet Zophorus, which is called in our Engliſhe tounge the frize. If any thing ſhalbe therin grauen or cut, then it ought to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth part higher the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Epiſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If nothing ſhalbe wrought win y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Frize the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> friſe be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fourth parte ſmaller then the Epiſtilium, Then deuide the Frize marked with F. into <hi>.7.</hi> partes, one ſuch parte adde therto for Cymatium, marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> G. let his Proiecture be alſo as muche as his height. That donne ye ſhall begin with the Coronix, marked with H. the which is the higheſt parte of the Trabeation. Ouer Cimatium, ſhalbe ſette Denticuli, marked with. I. whoſe height ſhalbe ſo much as the height of the myddlemoſt Faſcia, and his fillet to be the ſixt part of De<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuli, and aboue Denticuli, ye ſhall ſette Corona marked with K. and the height therof ſhalbe alſo like vnto the mydell Faſcia That height deuide into <hi>.4.</hi> partes, one of thoſe partes admit vnto Cymatium aboue Corona, the Proiecture of the Denticuli and Corona with Cymatium, hangeth ouer ſo much as the frize is in height, if the frize be the fourthe part diminiſhed. Thus writeth oure Author Vitruuius. Ouer Corona ſhalbe ſet Sima, marked with L. whoſe height ſhalbe the eight part higher then Corona, with his Cimatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his Edge at the toppe to be the Sixte part of Sima added therto, the Proiecture to be like vnto his height and ſo endeth the meaſures of Ionica.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus haue ye endid at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hieſt part of Trabeationis whoſe marke is H. Regula the edge of Sima marked L. Cymatium, Corona, marked K. added ouer the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mutilos, &amp; his Capital, Denticulus, marked I. Zophorus, marked. F Cimatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marked G. EPISTYLIVM marked A. Cimatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marked B. Faſcia prima, marked C. Faſcia Secu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da marked D. Faſcia Tertia marked E. CAPI<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TVLI, marked T. Cymatium. Abacus, marked V. Frons Voluta, marked X. Aſtragalus. COLVMNA, vpon the pillor noted Scapus, marked R Apophigis ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior. Apophigis Inferior. BASIS, marked M. Torus marked O. Regula, Scotia, Superior, marked P. Regula, Aſtragalus Primus, Aſtragalus Secundus marked Q Regula, Scotia, Inferior, Regula. Plinthus, marked N. Coronix, marked C. Regula. Cimatium marked H. Corona, marked I. Regula, in the finiſhed piller is added Echinus, Regula Sima, marked K Aſtragalus marked L Regula. Quadratum. Seſquialtera. BASIS, of the pedeſtalle mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked B. Regula, Cimatium inuerſa addid Regula Aſtragalus marked D. Sima Reuerſa mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked E. Regula, Torrilus, marked. F. Plinthus Primus marked G. Aſtragalus, Regula, Plin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus inferior being added vnto the Baſe of the pedeſtall for to increaſe his height and alſo for an other purpos moſt neſseſeary if the pillor ſtand on the ground and no ſtepes vnder the pedeſtall in the which bodye of the pedeſtall is demonſtrated Ichnographia, where in I begane and alſo make an ende</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> CORYNTHIA
<pb facs="tcp:1835:17"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram and illustration of Corinthian column</figDesc>
                     <head>CORYNTHIA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:18"/>
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:1835:18"/>
               <head>HERE BEGINETH THE PILLOR that was founde in Corinthia, by Callimachius the excellent Architect of Corinthe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O beginne with the Pedeſtal of Corinthia, ye ſhal enter thus, The flat ſtone or body of the Pedeſtal ſhalbe a ſquare &amp; <hi>.2.</hi> third partes in height the which is marked with A. whoſe height ye ſhal deuide into <hi>.7.</hi> partes, adde ſuch a part vnto the Baſe of the Pedeſtall, marked with B, and aſmuche for the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nix, whoſe marke is C. Then deuide the Baſe of the Pedeſtall marked with B. into <hi>.7.</hi> partes, Geue one vnto Cymatium, marked with D. and one vnto Aſtragalus, with his Regula, marked with E. Then geue <hi>.2.</hi> vnto Syma reuerſa marked with F. with his fillet, Then geue one part vnto Torus, marked with G. the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes admitte vnto the higheſt Plinthus, marked with H. the Proiecture, of this Baſe is like vnto his height The other Plinthus, is added therunto, the cauſe wherof, is mencioned and declared before in Ionica, The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuide Coronix, marked with C. into <hi>.10.</hi> partes Geue vnto Cymatium aboue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with. I <hi>.3.</hi> partes of the which his fillet ſhall haue <hi>.1.</hi> part Then admit alſo <hi>.2.</hi> partes to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona, marked with K. and alſo <hi>.2.</hi> partes vnto Syma and his fillet or edge marked with L. the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes geue vnto Cymatium with his edge marked with M. and the tenth parte admit vnto Aſtragalus &amp; Regula, marked with N. vnder Cymatium, the Proiecture ye ſhal make like vnto their height ſauing onely Corona, whiche ought to hange ouer <hi>.2.</hi> third partes more then his height the which is a beautie vnto the whole Coronix and ſo endeth the meaſures &amp; Proiectures, therunto belonging.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>BASIS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow ye ſhal finde the meaſures of the thicknes of the pillor, which is the Diameter, as doth follow, deuide the bredthe of the boddye of the Pedeſtal into <hi>6.</hi> partes, wherof the diameter or thicknes of the piller ſhalbe <hi>.4.</hi> ſuch parts &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> height of the pillor ſhalbe <hi>9.</hi> Diameters, wherof the Capitall ſhal haue <hi>.1.</hi> Diameter, for his height, &amp; alſo the height of the Baſe ſhalbe halfe a Diameter, which baſe is marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> O whole height ye ſhall deuide into <hi>.4.</hi> partes wherof the Plinthus, marked with P. occupieth <hi>.1.</hi> part. The other <hi>.3.</hi> partes deuide into <hi>5.</hi> parts. Geue vnto Torus, aboue which is marked with Q. one part, &amp; the Torus, beneth ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forth part greater the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Torus aboue, &amp; is marked with R. that which remaineth betwen the <hi>.2.</hi> Torus deuide into <hi>.2.</hi> partes, of the higheſt part ye ſhall make Trochilus, marked with S. wherof the Aſtragalus, ſhalbe the ſixte part, and his edge ſhalbe half his height, the other edge that lieth vnder the highe Torus, ſhalbe in height the third parte more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the height of the other edge. The ſecond part that remaineth is for the nethermoſt Trochilus or Scotia, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with T. whoſe Aſtragali, ſhall alſo be in height the ſixte part of Trochilus, and his edge ſhalbe halfe his height, the other edge that lieth on the nether moſt Torus, ſhalbe in height <hi>.2.</hi> third partes of the height of Aſtragali, the Proiecture of this baſe is thus. If this pillor ſtande vppon any other pillor, then ſhall the Proiecture therof be like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Proiecture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baſe of Ionica, &amp; if this piller ſtand vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or being alone by himſelf the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal this Proiecture of the Baſe be like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Proiecture, of the Baſe of Dorica, &amp; thus endeth the Baſe of Corinthia.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1835:19"/>
                  <head>SCAPVS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the Baſe or foote of the piller ye ſhall ſette Scapus, marked with V. whoſe height is <hi>.7.</hi> Diameters and a halfe, whoſe thicknes is diminiſhed the ſixte part of the toppe of Scapus, vppon either ſide half a parte as is before ſayde vppon the third part of the height of Scapus, ye ſhall make the half compas, through the which ye may finde a faire dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing as I haue ſaid before in Thuſcana, Dorica, and Ionica. If this piller be garniſhed and filled with Canaliculi, and Striges, whiche Vitruuius calleth Femora, there ſhalbe <hi>.28.</hi> in number rounde about the pillor. The meſures of them I haue before reherſed in the Ionica, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing onely from the third part of the pillor downewardes, Aſtraguli be made and ſet vpright round aboute the piller within the Canaliculi, the maner therof you ſhall finde in the ground plot, the which ſtandeth here betwene the <hi>.2.</hi> pillers &amp; is marked with X. The Proiecture, of Them doth anſwer iuſtly with the thicknes of the pillor: at the toppe of the piller ſhalbe made Aſtragalus &amp; his edge, the which ſhalbe the twelfte parte of a Diameter in height. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture therof is ſomuche, as the piller is diminiſhed on either ſide, and thus finiſheth Scapus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CAPITAL.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F this Capitall, Vitruuius maketh mencion in his fourth boke and firſt chapiter vppon the ſaid Scapus, which is the body of the piller, ye ſhal ſet the Capital being a Diameter in height, and is marked with Y. that height deuide into <hi>.7</hi> partes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit one vnto Abacus, marked with A. the which part ye ſhal deuide into <hi>.3</hi> partes geue <hi>.1.</hi> vnto Cimatium and his edge, the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes geue vnto Plinthus, the other <hi>.6.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that remained from the Abacus downewardes, deuide into <hi>.3.</hi> partes, geue one part vnto the ſhorteſt leaues and alſo one other to the height of the myddle leaues The third part is left for the height of Clauiculi, Vitruuius calleth it in the makinge of the Capitale of Ionica, Voluta, and is in this Capitall marked with B. being that which goeth out of Caulis, and turneth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>4</hi> Corners of the Abacus and they be in nomber <hi>.8.</hi> rounde about the Capital, the which cloſeth togither at the <hi>.4.</hi> corners of the Capitall, alſo there be other ſmaller, that are called Helices, the which ſpringe out of that which is the budde or Caules, and growe vpwardes right vnder the Abacus and haue but halfe the height of the other greater Helices, or Volutas and alſo <hi>.8</hi> of them be rounde about growinge alſo <hi>.2.</hi> and <hi>.2.</hi> togithers vnder the <hi>.4</hi> forefronts of the Aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, ouer the whiche ſtandeth the flower or Roſe in the myddell of the Abacus whoſe height is equall with the thiknes or height of Abacus, being <hi>.4.</hi> roſes or flowers in no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber in the <hi>.4.</hi> frontes of the Abacus. Alſo vnder the Abacus is a certaine ſquare edge named Tenia, whoſe height is half ſomuche, as the Abacus is in height, his Proiecture anſwereth to the thicknes of the pillor or Scapus, beneth: the which is the Diameter, Concerning the other Proiectures, they beginne thus. The Proiecture of the Abacus anſwereth &amp; is like vnto the Proiecture of the Plinthus of the Baſe or foote of the piller, and ſailleth ouer ſome what more then the Plinthus. Nowe to knowe how muche the Abacus hangeth ouer more then the Plinthus of the Baſe of the pillor, the which is ſhewed in the ground plotte named Ichnographia, and is marked with C. whiche grounde is to be made thus. Make you a rounde compas beinge of the thicknes of the piller then make a ſquare without that compas and alſo make an other compas, ſo grate as
<pb n="Xii" facs="tcp:1835:19"/> maye be, touching the <hi>.4.</hi> corner: of the ſayd ſquare, alſo ſet that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pas within an other ſquare, touchinge the <hi>.4.</hi> ſides of the great compas. So done we ſhall come to the right ground and faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Abacus, the which lieth on the vaſse or baſket, that was founde on the maydens to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be in Corinthe, as before is reherſed. Now let vs finiſhe and ende the ground plotte of the Capital That ſpace which is left bitwene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> two ſquares righte in the myddell of one of the ſides, deuyde you into <hi>.4</hi> partes Then take a paire of compas, ſetting the one poinct of the compas righte in the Corner of the greate ſquare beinge marked with <hi>.5.</hi> and the other poincte of the compas bring vnto the other corner of that ſquare marked with <hi>.6.</hi> and ſo drawe downewardes towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des <hi>.7.</hi> then bring that poincte of the compas, vppe agayne and ſet it in the place that it came from, and bringe downe the other poincte of the compas, from <hi>.5.</hi> vnto <hi>.7.</hi> and there it ſhall make a croſse. Then ſet the poinct of the compas, in the middes of the croſse and the other poinct of the compas ſette vppon the ſtrike betwen the <hi>2.</hi> ſquares, the which is marked with <hi>.3.</hi> and ſo drawe with the compas from <hi>.3</hi> to <hi>.5.</hi> and againe from <hi>.3.</hi> to <hi>.6.</hi> and vſe all the other ſides in lyke maner, and ſo through it ye ſhall knowe the trewe Proiecture. Nowe to knowe whither this grounde be vprighte or not, ye ſhall make a ſtrike ouerthwarte the greate ſquare from corner to corner, that line is named Diagonus, whoſe marke is C. being in lenght <hi>.2.</hi> Diameters So done is the grounde plotte of this Capitall, vpright and trewe, the which bringeth with it, his trewe Proiecture. Alſo ye ſhall perceiue in this Capital, marked with Y. that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of the Abacus, marked with A. is drawen a line by the ſide of the Capital, downewardes vnto the Aſtragali, that lieth vnder the Capitall, whoſe Proiecture, is ſo muche as the pillor is diminiſhed on the one ſide. Then ſhall the Proiecture of the Voluta or greate Helices, marked with B touche the line that is drawen by the ſide of the Capitall. The long leaues alſo vnder the Voluta, ſhall touche that line and in lyke caſe the ſhorte leaues. So done you haue your right and parfaicte grounde and the trewe vprighte meaſures of this Capitall with all his Proiectures. Touchinge this pillor that ſtandeth on the other ſide, the whiche is Antique: it ſtandeth, in an Arch triumphale, whoſe height is <hi>.29.</hi> modernelles and <hi>.15.</hi> minutes, the length of which elle, containeth <hi>.22.</hi> inches and a halfe. In Pantheon within Rome, and diuers other places in Italie are theſe pillers founde ſtanding in good eſtate. For this cauſe haue I ſette this Antique pillor here beſide that ye ſhould perceiue the beawtie whiche is in it, the whiche diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth littell from the firſte inuention of Vitruuius. The bodie of this ſaide pillor is garniſhed with Canaliculi, &amp; the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>.26.</hi> or <hi>28.</hi> whoſe Capital, is a Diameter, in height beſide the Abacus, and the Abacus added therto is the ſeuenth parte of a Diameter, his height to maintaine: the Antiques affirme that the firſte Author hath mente it thus the Capitall to be a Diameter in height beſide the Abacus, the height therof is before reherſed: alſo aſmuche as they haue added vnto the Capitall, ſomuche haue they diminiſhed of the height of Scapus, So that the pillor remaineth yet <hi>.9.</hi> Diameters in height, yea and ſome hath added the ſeuenth parte therto. Neuertheles it is beawtifull that they haue made, the other I do leaue to the diſreſciones of them whiche are or wilbe maiſters in this worthie ſcience, of Architecture. And thus finiſheth the order of this Capitall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>ARCHITRAVE, FRISE, AND CORNISHE.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1835:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touching the Architraue, friſe, &amp; Corniſh, bilo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging to Corinthia, Vitruuius, maketh no great mencion therof, Neuertheles he doth deſcribe the beginning of Mutuli to be neceſsarie in all Mullers to be made as ye may perceiue by the antique workes or buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. But this Architraue, friſe, and Corniſhe, ſhalbe like vnto that whiche was made for the Ionica, but vnto this Corniſhe, is added Echinus, marked with G. ſtanding betwixt Denticuli and Corona, being in height like vnto the vndermoſt Faſcia, marked with D. the Proiecture of the Corniſh, is increaſed ſomuche as Echinus is in height alſo vnto the Architraue is added vnder the ſeconde Faſcia, marked with E. Aſtragalus, being in height the eight parte of that Faſcia, make alſo that Aſtragalus, to be in height the eight part of the higheſt Faſcia, marked with F the whiche Aſtragalus, ſhalbe as it were certaine rounde beryes and the other Aſtragalus, that lieth vnder the myddle Faſcia, ſhalbe wrothonne like a wreath: as concerning the Friſe, it is to be ordered as before is mencioned in the meaſures of the Ionica, the proiecture of the foreſaid Architraue, is before reherſed in Ionica.</p>
                  <p>Now it behoueth to make mention of an other order and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men rule that the antiques hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue vſed in their time of buildinges appertaining to the whole Trabeations of the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, the meaſures is as hereafter followeth. Deuide the height of the pillor with the Baſe and Capitall, into <hi>.4.</hi> partes, the which whole Trabeationes, ſhalbe in height aſmuche as <hi>.1.</hi> of the <hi>.4.</hi> partes of the height of the pillor, and that height deuide into <hi>.10.</hi> partes, wherof ye ſhall geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto the height of Epiſtilium, the which we call Architraue, marked with .I. and alſo geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto the height of Zophorus, which we cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> freſe, marked with K. thoſe <hi>.4.</hi> which remaigne geue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corniſh, which Vitruuius called Coronices, marked with L. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning theſe <hi>.4.</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes that are geuen vnto Coronix, deuide you into <hi>.9.</hi> partes geue <hi>.1.</hi> vnto Cymatium marked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. M. and geue alſo <hi>2.</hi> parts vnto Echinus, with his edge whoſe marke is N. and alſo geue <hi>2.</hi> ſuch partes vnto Mutili, whiche is alſo named Modiglions, with his Cymatium marked with O alſo geue <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe partes vnto Corona, and his Cymatium, which is the forthe parte of Corona, and is marked with P. and the other <hi>.2</hi> partes geue vnto Syma, and his edge at the top which is the eight part of the whole Syma, which is marked with Q. The Proiecture, ſhalbe as before is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed ſauing onely that Mutili, ſhall hange ouer ſo farre as ye maye conueniently not hyddinge or ſhadowing his Cymatium the which doth anſwere right to the Proiecture of Corona. Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius declareth alſo the whole height of the Trabeationes, to be the fifthe part of the length of the pillor, &amp; ſo he writteth that it was made in Theatrum, wherof he maketh mention in his fifth booke and ſeuenth chapiter, this Trabeatione, is of that height the whiche he ſpake of and is marked with H. Now as touching the other ſide that ſtandeth ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> garniſhed pillor, that is alſo antique, it is inriched beawtifull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e hauinge in it Denticuli, Echinus, and alſo Mutuli, the which Vitruuius, doth not allowe ſaing in his forth booke and ſecond Chapiter, that Denticuli, &amp; Mutili ought not to ſtande, or be made in one Corniſhe or Coronix as ye may perceue by the other Coronices for that which ſtandeth in the myddes hath Mutili, and Echinus, and hath not Denticuli, alſo the other Coronices that ſtandeth ouer the Image hath in it Denticuli, &amp; Echi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus, but not Mutuli. So that which hath Mutili hath not Denticuli, and likewiſe that, whiche hath Denticuli muſt not haue Mutili, So that both theſe Coronices, haue their alteracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye both obſerue the Rule of Vitruuius, To the third Coronix, that the antiques, haue deuiſed in their
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:1835:20"/> buildinges they haue added Mutilos or Denticul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> according to their willes &amp; haue garn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap> it moſt triumphantly, as is manifeſt in diuers of their doinges. For the which they ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended. For Vitruuius ſaith, that Mutili ſhalbe a neceſsary thinge in all Coronices, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>teacheth alſo, that Denticuli ſhould be obſerued in Ionica, ſeing that it may be ſuffered i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nica, it is neceſsarye to be obſerued in Corinthia, and is made in Italie to their commend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> and fame, whoſe Proiecture therby doth more abound in beawtie. Thus ende the meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the makinge of Corinthia.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Euertheleſse I thinke it good to make a brief reheſall, retourning to the place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> I began at, &amp; alſo for that her is added diuers thinges, in the <hi>.3.</hi> chaunges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions in ingliſhe called architraue, friſe, and Corniſhe, the firſt and higeſt is R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> Sima marked. Q. C. matium Corona marked P. Cymatium Mutili marked O. Regula Ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> marked G. Aſtragalus &amp; Apophiges Denticuli Cymatium marked M ZOPHO<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> marked K. EPISTYLIVM marked I. Cymatium Faſcia marked F. with his Aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lus. Faſcia ſecunda marked E. Aſtragalus Faſcia tertia marked D. CAPITVLI m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> Y. Abacus marked A. Flos Voluta Maiores marked B. Voluta Minores. Folia Minorae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                        <desc>••••…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis Folia media. Folia ima, COLVMNA marked V. Aſtragalus Apophigis Superior <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ferior. BASIS marked O. Torus Superior marked Q. Regula, Scotia ſuperior. mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Regula Aſtragalus Primus, Aſtragalus Secundus Regula, Trochilus marked T. R. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Torus inferior marked R. Plinthus marked P. STYLOBATA, Coronicis ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> C. Cymatium marked I. Corona marked K Sima marked L. Cymatium marked Aſtragalus et Apophigis marked N. Quadratum Proportionis ſuper Bipartient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Tertia marked A. BASIS. to the ſame marked B. Cymatium Reuerſa marked D. Aſtragalus marked E. Sima Reuerſa marked F. Torulus marked G. Plinthus marked H. Aſtragalus et Regula, Plinthus inferior, laſt of all ICHNOGRAPHIA the ground plotte and foundation where with this worke began and alſo endeth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> COMPOSITA
<pb facs="tcp:1835:21"/>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram and illustration of Composite or Italic column</figDesc>
                     <head>
                        <hi>COMPO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SITA,</hi> OR ITALICA</head>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:1835:21"/>
               <head>¶COMPOSITA OR ITALICA THE TRYVMPHANT pillor, deuiſed by the Romanes, and ſetcheth his compoundes out of all the other before reherſed and written.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His pillor named Compoſita ſhalbe <hi>.10.</hi> Diameters in height, the which Dya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters are drawen ouerthwart the pillor, whereof the Capitall. is a wholle Dyameter in height, and Spira or Baſe is halfe a Diameter in height. Now as concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meaſures of the Pedeſtal, the bredth of the ſquare ſtone which is the bodye of the Pedeſtall ſhalbe doubled in the height, whiche Philander nameth the quadrante of the double proportio which is marked with A whoſe height ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.8.</hi> partes, one ſuche part ye ſhall adde to the height of his Coronix, marked with B. aſmuche you ſhall adde vnto his Baſe marked with C the other meaſures therin belonging ſhalbe as before is reherſed in the Corinthia, but in this Baſe is added Cyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium which lieth betwene Aſtragalus, &amp; the ſquare of the pedeſtall. Alſo Coronix is to be made as before is reherſed in Corinthia, but that in this, they haue added Denticulos, the which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene Cymatium and Echinus, throughe the which it mounteth to a forther Proiecture, the which the Romaynes haue done for the more pleaſure of the eye. As touchinge the bodye of the Pedeſtall they haue garniſhed it beautifully after diuers ſortes as by theſe finiſhed figures, ye maye perceiue. Nowe as the other Pedeſtalles before mencioned, were parted and deuided into ſo many partes as the pillors were Diameters in height, ſo is this Pedeſtall <hi>10.</hi> partes in height of the which, the Baſe occupieth the loweſt part, which is marked with C. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> double ſquare occupieth eight partes to his height, &amp; the tenth part is admitted to Coronix, marked with B.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>BASIS or SPIRA.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight and directely vpon the middell of the Pedeſtall ſhalbe ſet Spira or the Baſe of the pillor marked with D. whoſe height ſhalbe a Modulus, or halfe the thiknes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the pillor, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which height ye ſhal deuid into <hi>.6.</hi> partes geue one part vnto Torus aboue marked with E. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other <hi>.5,</hi> partes ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.3</hi> partes geue one part vnto Plinthus marked with F. the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes you ſhall deuide into <hi>.12</hi> partes wherof ye ſhal geue <hi>.5.</hi> partes vnto Torus the lower marked with G. geue alſo <hi>.2.</hi> partes to the two Aſtragali with their Rute whoſe marke is. H. the which edge or regula, is in height y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one half of <hi>.1.</hi> Aſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galus, geue alſo <hi>.1</hi> parte vnto that, which is marked with I. ſome name it Echinus, but the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing therof is not like Echinus, which lieth vnder the higher Torus, whoſe edge ſhalbe half a part. So that the higheſt Torus, &amp; Scotia, marked with K (the which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grekes call Troche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon) be very nigh of one height. The Proiectures of this Baſe are as before is reherſed in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SCAPVS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pillor ſhalbe <hi>.8.½</hi> Diameters in height, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which are drawen ouerthwart the pillor Now as touching the diminiſhing of the pillor aboue ye ſhall begin thus vppon the third Diameter there ye ſhal trie the middle of the pillor vnder the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Then deuid the thicknes of your pillor into <hi>.6.</hi> partes that is <hi>.3.</hi> on eche ſide of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middle of the pillor and ye ſhall ſette <hi>.5.</hi> ſuche partes for the thicknes of the pillor vnder the Capitall,
<pb facs="tcp:1835:22"/> which ſhalbe <hi>.2.</hi> and a halfe on eche ſide of the pillors myddel, from the which thiknes of the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor vnder the Capitall drawe both the ſides downe wardes perpendiculerly vppon the thirde Diameter wheron ye ſhall make a half cyrcle ſo greate as it maye be within the Diameter or thiknes of the pillor and it ſhall make on eche ſide a croſse ouer the perpendiculer line, meaſure from the croſses downewardes euen vpon the ſtrike of the half cyrcle or compas to the ouerth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wart ſtrike vpon the third Diameter &amp; deuide it into <hi>.6.</hi> partes, making <hi>.6.</hi> lines croſsing ouer the half cyrcle. And ye ſhall begin to drawe from the line marked <hi>.2.</hi> in the halfe cyrcle vnto the ouerthwart line at the toppe of the pillor marked with <hi>.2.</hi> and alſo from the line of the halfe cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle <hi>.3.</hi> drawe vpwardes perpendiculerly to the ouerthwarte ſtrike marked with <hi>.3.</hi> and ſo drawe vpwardes from <hi>4.</hi> to the ouerthwarte line marked <hi>.4.</hi> and ſo from <hi>.5.</hi> to <hi>.5.</hi> and alſo perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly drawe from <hi>6.</hi> to <hi>.6.</hi> Then take a rule and drawe from Diameter vnto Diameter downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, cloſing vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſide of the pillor as you may perceue by your figure, for I haue drawen &amp; cloſed the one ſide of the pillor, and the other ſide I haue lefte open that ye ſhould plainely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the working therof, the height of the Diameter, vnder the Capitall. ye ſhall deuide into <hi>12.</hi> partes the higeſt part ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.3</hi> equall partes, wherof ye ſhal geue <hi>.2.</hi> vnto Aſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galus, marked with L. and the third part ſhalbe geuen to the edge or Senta, which is marked with M. Alſo an other litle ſquare edge, which lieth vpon the Baſe being at the loweſt parte of Scapus ſhalbe in height like vnto Aſtragalus, at the top of Scapus. Concerning the garniſhing of the body of the pillor or Scapus, which oure authour calleth Canaliculi and Striges, the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques haue deuiſed ſo many ſundry ſortes, that herin the beawtye of them cannot be expreſsed. But amonge all other in Pantheon, is a pillor thus deuided. Ther be Canaliculi, round abought the pillor <hi>.24.</hi> in number, and eache of them in deuided into <hi>9.</hi> partes, of the whiche partes <hi>.4.</hi> is geuen vnto that, whiche oure authore nameth Stryges, vpon the which are made vpright in the middle therof Aſtragali, whoſe bredthe is <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe <hi>.4.</hi> partes, the other <hi>.2.</hi> partes are lefte for Stryges. So that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eache ſide of the Aſtragali, is left one part. The other <hi>.5.</hi> partes are left for Canaliculi, the which are hollowe inwardes. There is an other pillor, the which ſtandeth in Baſilia del foro tranſitorio, in Rome, the which is made much after one faſhion but that the Architect hath made his Canaliculi, ſomwhat biggar or largar. And that meaſure is thus. The pillor rounde about ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.28.</hi> or <hi>.32.</hi> partes The occaſion wherfore the number of thoſe doth differ, is for the placinge of the pillor ſtanding farre or nighe vnto the eye, for if this piller ſtande farre from the eye, there ſhalbe in number <hi>.24.</hi> and at the moſt but <hi>.26.</hi> And if the pillor ſtandeth nigh vnto the eye, there ſhalbe in number <hi>.28.</hi> or <hi>.30.</hi> and at the moſte, they made <hi>32.</hi> rounde about the pillor. Nowe eche of thoſe partes ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.3.</hi> partes, let <hi>.2.</hi> of thoſe partes be geuen to Canaliculi, the thirde parte ye ſhal deuide into <hi>.4.</hi> partes wherof geue <hi>.2.</hi> vnto Aſtragalus, and the other <hi>.2.</hi> that remaine, geue vnto the Strigeus, that ſtande on eche ſide of the Aſtragalus, the bredthe of eche of them is a parte, as ye may perceiue by this Ichnographia the whiche figure is and ſtandeth here betwene your <hi>2.</hi> pillors being your parfaicte ground of the bodye of the pillor or Scapus, whiche is marked with N. Thus finiſhinge the meaſures, the Prouctures ſhalbe as is before declared in making of the other pillors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>CAPITAL.</head>
                  <pb n="xv" facs="tcp:1835:22"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the toppe of Scapus, or pillor ſhalbe ſett the Capitall, whoſe height ſhalbe a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter, in the which Capitall Abacus with his long and ſhorte leaues, and his Caules out of the which ſpring the ſmaller Helices, be a portion taken from Corinthia. Alſo they haue brought to pas in this Capitall, Voluta and Echinus and Aſtragalus, with his rule, which is and are portiones of Ionica. The meaſures of this Capital are thus. From the pillor vpwardes to the toppe of the Capitall, that is marked with O whoſe height is a Diameter ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.7</hi> partes, wherof one ſhalbe geuen to Abacus, lung at the toppe of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, which is marked with P. the which partes, ſome Architecles haue added to the height of the Capitall, ſo that they haue made it to be in height a Diameter, and the ſeuenth parte of a Diameter, as before is reherſed in the Capitall of Corinthia, but ſo muche as they haue added to the height of the Capital, ſomuche haue they abated from the height of Scapus. Nowe of the forſaid <hi>.7.</hi> partes, doo remaygne yet <hi>6.</hi> the which ſhalbe reduced into <hi>.3</hi> partes, the one ſhalbe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the ſhorte leaues for their height, the ſecond part ſhalbe added vnto the height of the myddle leaues, and the third part vnto Voluta, marked with Q. as for the height of Echinus, marked with R. ſhalbe founde in the makinge of Voluta, as before is mencioned in Ionica. The Proiecture of this Abacus, whoſe marke is P. ſhalbe euen ſo muche as is the Proiecture of the Plinthus, the which is the loweſt parte of the Baſes, of the pillor euen as it is before ſaide in the ground plot of Corinthia, This done drawe from the vtter moſte of the Abacus, downewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des along by the ſide of the Capitall, vnto the vttermoſt of the Aſtragali lienge vnder the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, whoſe Proiecture, ſhalbe ſo muche as it is in height This done you ſhall cauſe Voluta to touche the ſtrike that you haue drawen by the ſide of the Capitall, and alſo the myddell and longe leaues vnder Voluta, ſhall haue their Proiecture to touche that line, and alſo the ſhorts leaues ſhall touche the ſame. This done ye haue the true meaſures and proiectures of this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, but there be diuerſe other beawtifull Capitalls, belonging to this pillor whiche hereafter more plainlye ſhall appere.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EPISTYLIVM.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He height of this Epiſtilium, or Architraue marked with. S. ſhalbe the thiknes of the pillor aboue vnder the Capitall, but if this pillor ſhall ſtande nighe vnto the eye then make the height therof, as before is reherſed in the other pillors, which height ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.7</hi> parts wherof one ſhalbe geuen vnto Cimatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> marked with T. the other <hi>.6.</hi> parts, deuided into <hi>.12.</hi> partes, geue <hi>.3.</hi> of them to the firſte Faſcia, marked with V. alſo geue <hi>.4.</hi> to the ſecond Faſcia, marked with X and geue <hi>5.</hi> vnto the thira Faſcia, marked with Y. vnder the ſecond and third Faſcia, ſhalbe added Aſtragali with Apophigis, to the garniſhing therof, the Proiectures, and meaſures ſhalbe as is before reherſed in Corinthia. Vpon the Epiſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye ſhall ſete Zophorus or Freſe marked A. wherin Mutili doth ſtand being in height like to Epiſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Mutili ſhall ſtande right ouer the pillor, their bredth ſhalbe the fifte parte leſse then the thicknes is of the pillor vnder the Capital, and they be marked with B. whoſe height ſhalbe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into <hi>.6.</hi> partes, Cimatium occupieth ſomuche as one of the <hi>.6.</hi> partes added for that whiche is the Capitall vnto the Mutili, &amp; is marked with C. the ſpace betwene the <hi>.2.</hi> Mutili, ſhalbe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche, as twyſe the bredth of Mutili, the Proiectures of Mutilos ſhalbe aſmuche as the wholle Mutili is in height. As touching the Coronices, the one ſide differeth from the other, both being
<pb facs="tcp:1835:23"/> fayre, take of them which pleaſeth your mynde beſt, their heightes ſhalbe like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> height of Mutilos. Then ye ſhall deuide that ſide ouer the pillor into <hi>.7.</hi> partes. Geue <hi>.4.</hi> vnto Corona, marked with D. alſo geue <hi>.2.</hi> vnto Cymatium, marked with E. the ſeuenth parte is lefte for Supercilium or Regula, marked with F. The Proiecture therof ſhalbe lyke their heightes the other ſide of the Coronix, ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiden which is marked with G. ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.2.</hi> equal partes, the loweſt parte ſhalbe geuen vnto Corona, the ſeconde parte ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.5.</hi> partes, geue one vnto that with his edge which is like to Echinus, geue <hi>.3.</hi> vnto Cimatiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and the fifthe parte, geue vnto Supercilium. The Proiectures of Mutilus with the Coronix ſhalbe ſomuche as they be both in height, Mutilus ſtanding in Zophorus, the antiques haue deuiſed for a commoditie and a beawtie to their edifices. But the cauſe why they were ſette in Zophorus with diuers other monuments therto belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging herafter ſhalbe declared as time ſhall ſerue. Thus haue I finiſhed for this time the figures, garniſhementes, and meaſures, of theſe fiue pilleres before ſpecified.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:1835:23"/>
               <head>¶ OF AN OTHER AVTENTIKE PILLER AND A neſceſsarie Companion to the before named pillers made by the Athenieus to his perfection named ATTICVRCA.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>diagram of Attic column</figDesc>
                     <head>ATICA</head>
                  </figure> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F this piller Plinius maketh reherſall and as he ſaith is a corner pillor, being foure ſquare, whoſe Diameter marked with A. (ſaith he) is like vnto the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d pillers, which he ſtandeth by but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Diagonall line marked B. he is thicker then the rounde pillers. It is that piller which Vitruuius nameth Atticurga or Attica, made by, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Atheniens, the which natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſed alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſures of Corinthia in their pillers. So that the Capital of this foreſaide piller, is much like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Capital of Corinthia. The Spira, or Baſe of the ſaide Attica, wherwith alſo they vſed to garniſh Corinthia, Vitruuius, alſo, witneſseth of ſuche a pillor, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and ſaith, that Spira attica ſhould be like vnto Spira or Baſe Ionica. Thus haue you all the maner and meaſures of pillers that anye notable maiſters of Architecture or Authours therof haue written. As in order do followe. Tuſcana conteineth in height <hi>.6.</hi> Diameters Dorica <hi>.7.</hi> Diameters in height. Ionica <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters in height, Corinthia <hi>.9.</hi> Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters in height, and Compoſita, contaigneth <hi>.10.</hi> Diameters in height, Nowe of this forſayde pillor Atticurga, I finde no mencion made of his height. But of the multitude of his Canaliculi, whiche be <hi>.7.</hi> on either ſide of the pillor. And as touchinge his height, wherof no mention is made, it is to be thought that he muſt beare ſuche height as the reſt of the pillors for Vitruuius ſaith that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> higheſt pillor paſseth not <hi>.10</hi> Diameters, in height ſo that his height may be agreable to the height of thoſe round pillors that are Ioyned with him, whither they be Compoſita or Corinthia, which I my ſelfe haue ſene in Rome in the arke triumphant of Seuerus, beinge ioined with Compoſita, alſo in Pantheon where his three ſides plainely are ſene, the fourth ſtanding in the wal, the Capital and baſe is like to the round pillers, wherwith he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth being Corinthia. The Proiecture of his baſe was like vnto Spira attica, the which is halfe a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulus, on either ſide of the Baſe, the which Vitruuius more plainly at large declareth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:24"/>
               <head>¶ THE CHAVNGE OF THE FIVE PILLERS ORDERLY to be vſed eche of them in his kynde whiche order of buildinges be named of Vitruuius as followeth PICNOSTYLOS, SISTYLOS, DIASTYLOS, ARIOSTYLOS, EVSTYLOS, whoſe pictures inſew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th demonſtrated in order.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe for ſomuche as I haue reherſed the beginning and the Inſtitution of this arte of Architecture, naming the writers and authors of the ſaid ſcience, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the meaſures geometrycall therto belonging in their ſimetries, with all their garniſhementes: it is therfore alſo requiſit to reherſe and to let you vnderſtand, by what meanes the order of the before named pillers ſhalbe altered in their ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, adding, or abating to or fro, euery of them accordingly as they ſhalbe placed, by whiche knowledge or like knowledges many may come to the righte perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vpon whiche occaſion it ſhalbe declared what mention Vitruuius doth make in the third boke and ſecond Chapiter &amp; alſo the opinion of Sebaſtianus Serlius and other vpon the ſame, how far and how nere the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ſhalbe ſet a ſunder: Saying that this order of Picnoſtylos ought thus to be made, that which is the ſpace betwene the <hi>.2.</hi> pillers ſhalbe a Diameter and a halfe the piller being in height <hi>.10.</hi> Diameters. Siſtylos is that which hath <hi>.2.</hi> Diameters betwixt the <hi>.2</hi> pillers, whoſe height ſhalbe <hi>9.</hi> Diameters and a halfe. Diaſtylos ſhall thus be made, the pillers ſhall ſtand <hi>.3.</hi> Diameters one from an other, whoſe height ſhalbe <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters and a halfe. Arioſtylos is that, which hath the ſpace or bredth betwene the pillers <hi>.4. 5.</hi> or <hi>.6.</hi> Diameters, and at the furdeſt <hi>.7.</hi> Diameters, the whiche pillers comonly are <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters in height: but in the Euſtylos the authors differ. the one ſaith that his meaſure is like Diaſtyli, and the other ſaith that it ought to be like Siſtyli, and ſo becauſe Diaſtyli is <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters and a halfe and Siſtyli <hi>.9.</hi> and a halfe, therfore oure authoure hath made betwene them both an vniformity, and cauſeth Euſtylos to be <hi>.9.</hi> Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in height. This done Areoſtyli is <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters in height. Diaſtyli <hi>.8.</hi> Diameters and a halfe. Euſtylos <hi>9.</hi> Diameters. Siſtyli <hi>.9.</hi> and a halfe, and Picnoſtyli <hi>.10.</hi> Diameters. Nowe like as Tuſcana, Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia, &amp; Compoſita, increaſe their heightes by Diameters, ſo do theſe <hi>.5.</hi> here before reherſed increaſe their heightes by Modulus or half Diameters, and you ſhal alſo garniſh &amp; faſhion them according to their lengthes, as I haue by their lenght ſhewed before their ſimilitude and ſtrength, whiche you ſhall ſee and perceiue more plainely in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations followinge.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>AREOSTYLOS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing Araeostyle (light-columned) spacing</figDesc>
                        <head>AREOSTYLOS</head>
                     </figure> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eginning with this firſt being Areoſtylos, as Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarianus ſaieth, ought to be in height <hi>.8.</hi> Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the diſtaunce betwene the <hi>.2.</hi> pillors to be <hi>4. 5.</hi> or <hi>.6.</hi> Diameters as is before reherſed, whiche piller for his ſtrength is likned or to be ſembled vnto Tuſcana neceſsary for all foundations and fortifications both to withſtande great forſe, &amp; ſupporte wayghtie burdens, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maiſter builder can vſe him, which is to be ſene in diuers places in Italie, calling it Ruſticke or Rughe hewed ſtone, and in other places to be otherwiſe garniſhed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:1835:24"/>
                  <head>DIASTYLOS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing Diastyle (board-columned) spacing</figDesc>
                        <head>DIASTYLOS</head>
                     </figure> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond order as I haue placed it, is that whiche Vitruuius calleth Diaſtylos, whoſe height (ſaith he) is <hi>.8</hi> Diameters and a halfe, and the diſtaunce betwene the <hi>.2.</hi> pillers ought to be <hi>.3.</hi> Diameters or <hi>.4.</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furdeſt. which pillor is likned vnto Dorica made to his perfection in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Mars. which alſo is a piller to garniſhe cyties and gates ſomwhat pleaſaunt and ſtronge as is to be ſene in diuers places, as alſo gates of pallaces with the vtter galleries.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>EVSTYLOS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing Eustyle (well-columned) spacing</figDesc>
                        <head>EVSTYLOS.</head>
                     </figure> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third order is that whiche Vitruuius calleth Euſtylos, the whiche oure Author hath brought to a vniformity, ſaying the piller to be in height <hi>.9.</hi> Diameters, &amp; the diſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwen the <hi>.2.</hi> pillers to be <hi>.2.</hi> Diameters &amp; a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as Guliheline Philander affirmeth, but at the furdeſt <hi>.2.</hi> Diameters and a halfe or <hi>.3.</hi> which piller is likned vnto Ionica builded to his parfection in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Diana &amp; Apollo &amp; to be vſed in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny meane edifices to be garniſhed accordinglye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SISTYLOS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing Systyle (close-columned) spacing</figDesc>
                        <head>SISTYLOS.</head>
                     </figure> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fourth order is that whiche Vitruuius cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Siſtylos, whoſe height (ſaith he, is) <hi>.9.</hi> diame<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters and a halfe, whoſe pillers ſtandeth diſtant one from the other <hi>.2.</hi> Diameters, or <hi>.2.</hi> and a halfe at the fourdeſt and after this maner it was made in the temple of Fortune, which piller is likned vnto Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia, whoſe meaſures are ſlender &amp; ſerueth to garniſh princes pallaces and for diuers other thinges neceſsarye whiche multitude nedeth not to be reherſed, but as time ſhall ſerue they maye be practiſed and brought in vre to diuers vſes moſt neceſsarie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1835:25"/>
                  <head>PICNOSTYLOS.</head>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram showing Pyknostyle (tight-columned) spacing</figDesc>
                        <head>PICNOSTYLOS</head>
                     </figure> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt &amp; laſt order is that which Vitruuius, calleth Picnoſtylos whoſe height ſaieth he is <hi>.10</hi> Diameters whoſe pillers ſtandeth diſtant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eche other a Diameter, &amp; a halfe or <hi>.2.</hi> at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt &amp; thus was it made in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Venus which piller is ſembled or to be compared vnto Compoſita hauing in it the full beawtie of al the forſaide meaſures and garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for al excellent artificers, beawtifully to ſet furth whether it be in golde or ſiluer or other riche ſtone or fine woodes in marketrey or imboſinge or caruing as ſhalbe thought pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; neceſsary for noble &amp; mighty pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces or for diuers other eſtates louers of excellency or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ninge.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ AN OTHER RVLE GEVEN BY VITRVVIVS for theſe three orders of pillers Dorica, Ionica, Corinthia, to be vſed as folowith.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow if you will begin with the order of Dorica, you ſhall deuide his height with the Baſe and Capitall into <hi>.15.</hi> partes, one of thoſe partes ſhalbe the height of the Baſe and aſmuche vnto the height of the Capital, whiche ſhalbe the Modulus of the worke. If it ſhalbe the order of Ionica, you ſhall deuide the height of Scapus, with the Baſe and Capitall into <hi>.8.</hi> partes and a halfe, and one of thoſe partes ſhalbe the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of the whole worke, whoſe Baſe ſhalbe a Modulus in height, his Capital ſhalbe as before is reherſed in Ionica<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> alſo if you will make an order of Corinthia, ye ſhall make it as I haue now reherſed of this laſte piller, ſauing onely that in the ſtede of the Capitall of Ionica, ye ſhall ſet the Capitall of Corinthia, which is a dyameter in height. Now ye ſhall vnderſtand that Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius doth not will Dorica, Ionica, and Corinthia, to ſtande one vpon an other but he willeth the Edifice to be all of Dorica, orels all of Ionica, or all of Corinthia, and they to ſtande one vppon an other, alway d miniſhinge, ſo that the higher they ſtand, the leſser or ſklenderer they muſte be, for, as he ſaieth, a tree is no where ſo greate as at the ground, and ſo groweth ſmaller and ſmaller vpwardes vnto the toppe. likewyſe, he willeth the loweſt pillor to be ſtrongeſt made v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the meaſure, as before is ſayd, and the ſecond pillor, that ſtandeth ouer him, both in height and bredthe ſhall diminiſhe his fourthe parte. And his Architraue, freſe or Corniſh ſhalbe in heigth the fiueth parte of the height of that piller, and ſo ſettinge the one vpon the other, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhinge after this ſayde order. Some of the antiques aforſaid haue obſerued theſe orders and meaſures, as Sebaſtianus, doth witneſse in his third boke and fourth Capiter that there are many edifices of the antiques wherin all the orders of theſe pillers haue bene ſette one vppon an other: garniſhing them accordinglye as it is yet to be ſene in the Amphitiatrum named Colloſseum in Rome whoſe excellent and praiſe worthy doing ſhalbe more plainely ſette fourth hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:1835:25"/>
               <head>¶ HERE IS AN OTHER NECESSARIE Rule appointed of Vitruutus for the diminiſhing of Scapus, vnder the Capitall by the increaſing of his height.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>table with ornate border</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell role="label">fotes</cell>
                              <cell role="label">diam</cell>
                              <cell role="label">pairt</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>15</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>6</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>5</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>20</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>6½</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>5½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>30</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>7</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>6</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>40</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>7½</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>6½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>50</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>8</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>7</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>60</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>8½</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>7½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>70</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>9</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>8</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>80</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>9½</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>8½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>90</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>10</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>9</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>100</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>10½</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>9½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>110</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>11</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>10</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                  </figure> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Itruuius, in his third booke and third Chapiter; ſainth thus if Scapus amounte in heighte from <hi>.15.</hi> fote vnto <hi>.20.</hi> the Dia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meter is to be deuided into <hi>.6.</hi> partes &amp; a halfe, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thicknes of the pillor vnder the Capitall, ſhalbe <hi>.5.</hi> and a halfe. And if Scapus, Amounte from <hi>.20.</hi> vnto <hi>.30.</hi> foote then ſhall the Diameter be deuided into <hi>.7.</hi> partes, wherof <hi>.6.</hi> partes ſhalbe the thicknes of the pillor vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Capitall and ſo augmenting and diminiſhing after this order vntill Scapus, if it were poſsible, ſhoulde amounte to the number of <hi>110.</hi> foote whiche is the ende of this table that ſtandeth here beſide wherin ye maye perceiue in euery <hi>.10.</hi> foote increaſsinge in height doth ſhew the thicknes of Scapus vnder the Capitall, ſo that the <hi>110.</hi> foote in height of Scapus, the Diameter to be deuided into <hi>.11.</hi> partes, then ſhalbe the thicknes of Scapus, vnder the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall <hi>.10.</hi> of thoſe <hi>.11.</hi> partes, &amp; ſo furth if nede ſhall require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ AN OTHER EXAMPLE TO BE obſerued very neceſsary for the maiſter builder or Architecte that is for the inlarging of the Epiſtilium, when the pillor amounteth to certaine heightes.</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>table with ornate border</figDesc>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>15</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/13</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>20</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/13</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>25</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/12</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>30</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/12</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>35</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/11</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>40</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/11</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>45</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/10</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>50</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/10</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>55</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/9</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>½</hi>
                              </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>60</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell>
                                 <hi>1/9</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                  </figure> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Itruuius in the latter ende of his tird boke declaring when the piller that is to ſaye Baſe Scapus, and Capitall amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from <hi>.15</hi> foote to <hi>.20.</hi> fote in height, then ſhal the height of the wholle pillor be deuided into <hi>.13.</hi> partes, on ſuch a part ſhalbe the height of the Epiſtilium, alſo if the pillor do increaſe from <hi>20.</hi> to <hi>.25</hi> fote then ſhall the piller be deuided into <hi>12.</hi> partes and a half wherof the height of the Epiſtilium ſhall occupie one ſuche part, alſo if the piller ſurmount fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>.25.</hi> to <hi>.30.</hi> the height of the pillor muſt be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into <hi>.12</hi> partes wherof the height of the Epiſtilium, ſhall occupie one ſuch part &amp; ſo forth as the colume increaſeth in height ſo increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the height of Epiſtilium, as in this table is euidenly diſcuſsed the encreaſing from <hi>.15.</hi> to <hi>.60.</hi> foote increaſed by <hi>.5</hi> at ones the whiche pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of <hi>.60.</hi> foote in height ſhalbe deuided into <hi>.9.</hi> partes, where of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occupieth for his height one ſuch part, and ſo paſsing forward as neceſsitie ſhall requyre in order as is before mencioned.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1835:26"/>
               <p>Therbe alſo diuers other orders of meaſures and example that the Antiques alwayes vſed in their times, which ſhoulde be to tedious for the hearer, and to long for the Reader, hauing no fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures out of the whiche ſpringeth both deſire and alſo encouragment to the ſame. Thus ending this treatie of the Introduction and meaſures of theſe forſayd pillers, whiche are the original firſt grounds and entring into this noble ſcience of Architecture, practiſed and alowed by right mighty and worthye potentates, and Emperours for perpetuall memorye of their victorious and triumphant feates, the Elegance therof, of all antiquitie hath bene and yet preſentely is as a parfaicte example and a myrroure to behold, lerne and take trewe meaſures, aſwell to all ſuche, as delight in durable Edifices and buildinges, as alſo to all noble parſonages and Architectures, whiche do or ſhall take pleaſure to erecte &amp; builde the like to any beawte and perfection accord nge to the deuiſe and myndes of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Authours Vitruuius, and Sebaſtianus Serlius, to whom vndoubtedly, the praiſe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation is chiefly to be attrybuted and geu n. I ſubmyt my trauel, vnto allother that in any parte be or ſhalbe of more parfaict &amp; deper learninge, knowledge and experience, and of like well wylling affection, wherwthi I do offer this my poore atemptes and ſmal trauailes.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ IMPRINTED AT LONDON IN Fleteſtrete nere to Sainct Dunstans church by Thomas Marſhe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1835:26"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
